All right.
Today we're going to talk about linked
planar 3SAT.
This is an extra strong version
of planar 3SAT
compared to the version
we saw last lecture.
It's relatively new -- it’s
by Pilz in 2018 --
and it's motivated
by proving Super Mario Brothers
is NP-hard.
So let me first talk about a proof
that Super Mario Brothers is NP-hard.
This started in 2012 and then I think
it was finally finished in 2014.
So here you see some press we got: “Science
proves old video games were super hard.”
This is justifying “Nintendo
hard” games by proving them NP-hard.
Later in the class,
we're going to actually prove
Super Mario Brothers is PSPACE-complete.
But today, we're just thinking about
good old NP-hardness.
This proof will apply to the original
Super Mario Brothers,
Super Mario Brothers Lost Levels (which
is Super Mario Brothers 2 in Japan),
Super Mario Brothers 3, and
Super Mario World.
So the reduction is from 3SAT.
This was done before we had
linked planar 3SAT and the point of
linked planar 3SAT is to make this
proof easier.
But first let me tell you the
regular proof.
So of course, with 3SAT, we've got
some variables, we've got some clauses.
And the idea is that
Mario is going to traverse this network
connecting each variable to the clauses
that it appears in
by traversing these tunnels.
So we start up at the start.
And then in the first variable gadget,
Mario is going to make a decision
whether to set x to true or false,
let's say setting it to true.
Then Mario's intended
path is to go and visit
all the clauses that contain x
because they are now satisfied
and it's going to do something
to unlock those clauses.
Then it gets routed to the
next variable.
If instead Mario had chosen not x,
it would have set all the clauses
that have not x to be satisfied and
then go to the same variable choice.
And then you make a choice for y.
Say you choose not y.
Then you make a choice for z.
Say you choose z as true.
And then at the end, whether you choose z
or z-bar, they both route to this common
path, which is to check all of the
clauses and you can get to the finish
of the end of the level
if and only if
each of these clauses has been satisfied
like it is in this example.
So that's what we'd like to build.
Now let me show you the gadgets that go
in these two boxes, variables and clauses.
So this is the original version
that appeared in 2012.
We have a variable where
we're using this idea of long falls.
So if Mario falls really far,
he can't jump back up.
This is actually not the interesting
long fall.
The interesting one is falling left
or falling right here.
If these are long enough,
then once Mario chooses the true
path or the false path,
they can't undo that choice.
I think this-- the purpose here is
there's actually two ways to get to
this variable gadget, depending whether
the previous variable was true or false.
So those are the two entrances,
and that's the variable, that works fine.
Then there's this clause.
The idea is that
these are the three places,
the three literals of the clause.
So those are connected to
some variable gadget up above.
And if Mario can get here, hop on
the Koopa, send the shell running,
it breaks these blocks, and goes out
the hole of this gadget or the next one.
So if you can get to
any one of these turtles, you're happy.
Because of this long fall, Mario can't,
like, come in here and go back up there.
And if you force Mario to be big,
he won't be able to get through here
and cheat.
So the idea is you come here,
hit one of the turtles, and later
you'll be able to go through this path
if and only if the clause is satisfied.
Good? All right,
except we forgot what Super
Mario Brothers 1 mechanics were,
and in fact, for Super Mario Brothers 1
these blocks I think would shift,
but they don't actually get broken
by turtle shells.
That is Super Mario Brothers 3.
Super Mario Brothers 3,
this gadget works.
But in Super Mario Brothers 1,
we need something else.
The same idea works
with Super Mario World.
A little different,
but same setup up here.
But here we have a question
block that-- and shells will
enable the thing inside the question
block.
And in particular, Super
Mario World has a POW block
which will turn all these coins into
walls or bricks for 10 seconds
or so and long enough for Mario
to make it through.
If Mario can hit one of the shells
and set up the POW block for later,
then Mario can come and get it
and run across and check the clause.
Okay. What about Super Mario Brothers 1?
For this we're going to use--
we're also going to use question blocks.
But it's a little trickier because,
yeah,
we're not even going to use
turtle shells in this proof.
We're just going to have a star available
in each of these question blocks.
So if Mario can satisfy
one of the literals,
there'll be a star bouncing around
back and forth here.
Stars give Mario invincibility
so you can--
Mario can later, when checking the
clause, get the star
and survive this path of doom
because they're invincible
for just long enough
to get through this clause,
then check the next one, and so on.
Okay, so this is the working version
that happened in 2014
for Super Mario Brothers 1.
So that's variables. Oh, right.
There's a slight catch,
which is in real Super Mario Brothers
you also have these fun glitches
like the ability to wall jump.
I've actually done this in
Super Mario Brothers.
It's not super hard
but definitely requires
a bit of luck and/or
tool assisted speedruns.
If you jump just at the right time
when you hit a wall,
you can bounce off of it and that
prevents our long falls from working.
But there's an easy fix, which is
for every long fall we add some ceiling.
And it's not a-- if you jump up this
wall, you won't be able to get
right in that center,
especially if you make this wider.
But I think even with this width.
There's more fun glitches,
like the ability
to run through horizontal walls.
This doesn't work vertically.
But yeah, it's crazy
what you find you can do.
I mean, there's very exhaustive--
in the speedrunning community,
there's an exhaustive set of people
trying to find the best ways
to run every level,
finding all these crazy glitches.
These are very hard for humans to do.
They require precise timing
of hitting the left and right button.
But we can fix this too, by whenever we
have a wall that you could run through,
you also put a bunch of enemies so you'll
take damage if you try to run through it.
And if you have enough damage,
you will die.
So these are working around the glitches
that we know in Super Mario Brothers.
All right.
So that's how we do a variable --
see it here --
how we do a clause.
So far, so good, except you see
lots of crossings in this diagram.
We're not reducing from planar 3SAT
because it won't help us --
I'll talk about that in a second --
we're reducing from 3SAT.
So these connections here between a
variable and a clause are actually doubled.
It's more like the colored edges here.
So you'll be coming through here
visiting this part of the clause,
which is really going to be upside down
because all the literals are on
the bottom of the figure and then
coming back on a separate path.
So at each of these crossings
between the colored lines
we need a crossover gadget.
And I'm going to show you the
crossover gadget just to tell you why
we want to get rid of them
because they're really annoying.
But at each crossover
we only need it to work
in a single direction.
So blue is always going to go
in this direction,
purple is always going to go
in this direction, for example.
In this place, purple will always
go in this direction.
So each path only needs to
work in one direction.
We also know an ordering on the paths.
We know that the blue path,
if it's used,
will happen before the purple path
because we're choosing variables in order.
For each of these colored intersections
we can figure out which is first.
So that's going to be useful.
Here is the original crossover
gadget from 2012.
It has a couple of maybe bugs,
but this gives you the high level idea.
You can either go up through this gadget
if you're big Mario,
you can break these blocks, get through,
and maybe you can't get on this path.
Although I think maybe you can.
In fact, if you duck and jump enough
times it might be possible.
On the other hand,
if you come from the left,
take damage from this goomba,
then you're small enough,
you can get through here, get a
mushroom out of this question block,
and then -- which is necessary,
you have to take it because otherwise
you won't be able
to get through here -- and leave.
Here is the fixed version
that eventually appeared,
where we've added some more wiggling
here for a couple of reasons.
One is it's not possible
for big Mario to get through there.
And the other is--
We added a long fall just to make sure you
can't come backwards through this gadget.
I think the other issue is that
depending on how you hit this question
block, the mushroom may have gone left.
And in this previous gadget,
it may have fallen in here,
which would-- could do weird things.
So this is the "cleaned up" version.
It's still quite complicated.
There is some leakage here,
which is -- let's see --
if you go from horizontal to vertical,
if both are traversed.
So if you first come through here
and later come this way,
you'll be able to go up.
And that's the leakage
we maybe don't want.
But you can avoid that
by just ordering these paths correctly.
If you guarantee in the ordering
that you do the horizontal
before you do the vertical,
then there won't be any leakage.
Okay. So this was just to remind you
how painful crossover gadgets are.
Lots of intimate constructions
here that we'd like to avoid.
So can we do
a stronger version of Planar 3SAT
that doesn't need crossovers?
All right. So now let's go back to last
lecture and remember what Planar 3SAT says.
So this is Planar 3SAT theorem:
3SAT remains NP-hard
when a particular graph is planar.
The graph is-- consists of
two parts, let's say.
There's a variable clause
bipartite graph.
So this is all of the connections between
variables and the clauses they appear in.
So that's basically this
part of the graph,
below this line and above this line.
And then that's the base version,
that graph is planar.
But we got a somewhat stronger version,
which is that that graph plus a cycle
through all the variables in some order
that together that graph is planar.
And there are some other
fun constraints we got.
One of them,
it can be phrased this way
that all of the pos-- so each edge
in this bipartite
graph is either positive or negative,
meaning the the variable appears
in its positive form or its negated form.
And you can guarantee
that the positive edges are, say, interior
to this variable cycle and the negative
edges are exterior to this variable cycle.
And this is actually
what we were calling planar monotone [rectilinear]
3SAT, where you have a horizontal line
that represents the cycle
through all the variables
and all the positive clauses appear
above all the negative clauses below.
So in fact this constraint
in this formulation with this cycle
implies that the clauses are monotone,
either all positive or negative,
because every clause is either going to be
inside the cycle or outside the cycle.
Here is a little picture.
Big cycle through all the variables
which we are drawing with circles,
and then we have some clauses inside --
those are going to be positive --
some clauses outside --
those are going to be negative
because these edges are negative.
Cool. So that was the good news.
The annoying thing,
if you look at this construction, is--
Okay, we have the bipartite graph
in the middle.
We also want to have a path
through all the clauses
because we need to be able
to traverse the clauses and check them all
in some order.
So that's good because we-- oh, sorry,
we have a cycle through all the variables.
That's also useful
because we need to come into the variable,
do some stuff
and then go to the next variable
and go to the next variable.
So we actually need a path
on the variables as well,
but then we need a connection
from the last variable
to the first clause, and we need a
path through all the clauses.
And that seems
problematic because last time
we also mentioned this positive result.
I guess is good news or bad news
depending on what you're thinking about.
It's bad news for hardness.
3SAT can be solved
in polynomial time if,
almost the same setup,
we have the bipartite graph, plus
we have a cycle through all the vertices,
plus we have a path
through all the clauses.
This is basically what we want
in the Mario Brothers hardness proof.
This is easy,
because your graph has to look like this.
Once you have a cycle
through all the variables
and a path through all the clauses,
that means all the clauses are on
the same side of the cycle, either outside
or inside doesn't really matter.
And that can be solved with dynamic
programing when they're all on the same side.
We really need clauses on both sides.
So how could we possibly fix this?
For the Mario proof,
there's one little thing,
which is that we don't need a cycle here.
We can have
just a path through all the variables.
And so it might seem
like a pretty minor difference,
it's one edge.
Things are a little worse,
we also need an edge from the last
variable to the first clause.
So we're basically taking one edge
out of this and putting it somewhere else.
But it turns out that problem is hard.
So that is linked planar 3SAT.
Let me
define it for you.
All right, so here's the base version.
I'm going to define
a bunch of extended versions as well.
Again, pretty similar setup, 3SAT
remains NP-hard when some graph is planar.
That graph primarily consists
of variable clause bipartite graph, but
we get a cycle
and this one cycle visits all
of the variables in some order
and then all of the clauses in some order.
This is almost exactly, it's even a little
bit more than what we need for Mario.
For Mario, we need to be
we need to pass through the variables,
then an edge from the last variable
to the first clause,
then a path through all the clauses.
And then we don't need
a final closing edge.
But what linked planar 3SAT says is
even with the final closing edge,
so even if you have to finish the game
where you started,
3SAT is hard when
that whole thing is planar.
Which is super cool.
Questions?
All right.
So this is what we really wanted
when we were writing this proof,
almost.
It turns out there a couple of catches in
applying this theorem to this proof,
which I will get to.
But first I'm going to prove this theorem
to you
from reduction from planar 3SAT
and also tell you some other versions
that are hard.
So one additional constraint you can make
is that the formula is monotone,
so every clause is all positive or all
negative, and you can require that
every variable appears
at most three times.
A different constraint you can add
is what I call sidedness.
It's not defined in the paper.
It's this constraint:
Positive/negative edges are on opposite
sides of not the variable cycle,
but of the cycle that visits
all the variables and all the clauses.
So positive/negative edges
are on opposite sides
of the cycle.
Crucially,
this does not imply
monotone in this problem.
I think maybe I have a figure for this.
So we have--
this is a nice--
some nicer examples of regular planar 3SAT
with the variable cycle
and linked planar 3SAT
with the variable and then clauses cycle
so that the dotted thing
is the added cycle.
The whole structure is planar.
Some notation, which is
the legend up there:
the filled circles are clauses,
the empty circles are variables,
the blue arrows are the positive edges.
And in some of the later figures there,
the colors are going to disappear,
so I want to introduce
also this arrow notation.
If the edge points to
the variable, then it's positive.
Sorry:
if it points to the clause, it's positive;
if it points to the variable,
it's negative.
Those are two ways to communicate
the parity on the edges,
and here you see there's no particular
rhyme or reason to the coloring.
But this is mainly to
illustrate what a variable
cycle looks like
versus what a variable-and-then-clauses
cycle looks like.
You can see you can have edges inside,
you can have edges outside.
That's what makes this problem not easy.
You can have in the general form,
you can have positive and negative edges
inside and outside.
Now I'm going to
change the coloring, change the instance
and the clauses
to one where
all the edges-- Over here, all the edges
inside are going to be negative,
all the edges outside are positive.
And then if you look
at the corresponding clauses,
because the inner clauses here
have to be all negative,
and the outer clauses
have to be all positive,
and so you get monotone 3SAT
just from that sidedness constraint.
Whereas over here
it's a little different
because while we have positive edges
inside, negative edges outside,
clauses span both inside and outside.
Am I pointing at the right thing?
Yes, this is the clause.
Here is a positive edge on the inside and
an incident negative edge on the outside.
So this is sided, but it's not monotone.
And with planar 3SAT--
with linked planar 3SAT,
you can either assume monotone
or you can assume sided, but not both.
I wanted to mention one other fun fact
while we're on this topic,
which is
you can assume
each clause
has at most two
incident edges
on each side of the cycle.
We can't assume that they're
all on one side or all on the other.
But in fact,
we can assume that's never the case.
Every clause has,
at least-- at most two edges on each side.
Can't guarantee it has at least
one on each side,
because there are some 2SAT clauses.
But that's what we have.
Some other versions.
E3SAT.
E3SAT is where every
every clause has exactly three literals.
That's
not super useful for video game proofs,
but it's nice to know.
We can also do 1-in-3SAT,
and for 1-in-3SAT
we don't need negations,
just like in the planar case.
And I have here a note
which is, for linked
planar 3SAT, E4SAT,
monotone E3SAT,
and the big one is sided
monotone 3SAT, are all in P.
So these are three different problems.
Each of them can be solved in polynomial
time.
These two, I think because your formula's
basically always satisfiable
and this one because
dynamic programing, I believe.
So these are things we need to avoid.
We really can't assume in particular sided
plus monotone.
I'm stressing this
because we'd really like it for the
Mario proof, but
problem's not hard without it
so-- problem's not hard with
those constraints.
So we're going to throw away
monotonicity and keep sidedness.
But before I go back to Mario,
I want to prove
or show you the proofs of this
main claim and a bunch of these
in varying amounts of detail.
So let's start with the big idea.
This is Pilz's cool idea that we
we're going to take our cycle
and we, you know, normally
we think of a cycle
as like a horizontal line or something
that's really hard to work with.
It's hard to connect everything.
Instead, we're going to take our cycle
and wrap it around itself
like a jelly donut or a spiral
so that we get
lots of stuff next to each other.
And we're going to break the cycle here
conceptually between
where the clauses are
and where the variables are.
I think here and here.
And you can look, like, let's follow
the dashed lines of the variables.
They go around and around
and around and around and they end here.
Then we switch to clauses and we visit
all the clauses in order in the opposite,
like counterclockwise. One was
clockwise, the other was counterclockwise.
And then we come back around.
But still a planar cycle, right?
And this is cool
because it puts variables and clauses
next to each other in like a grid.
So we're going to work with this
shaded grid,
we're going to ignore all the other stuff.
These are just going to
be wraparound edges.
All the action, all the other edges
are going to be in this shaded area.
So we can just think of there
being vertical lines
that alternate
between variables and clauses.
So this is our scaffold. Now
we're going to reduce from planar
monotone [rectilinear] 3SAT.
Probably overkill, but it gives some
of the more general results.
And in that planar setup
you're going to have some edge
which doesn't cross other edges
from the instance,
the SAT instance, but it is going to cross
some of these vertical lines.
And so we're going to make that planar
by subdividing
this edge into some pattern
like this in a very simple way.
So we wanted this variable x
to communicate with this clause c.
And what we're going to do
is copy x to here,
and copy x to here,
and now they're adjacent and we're happy.
So if we're in the end goal,
this is a copy of x
and then if you wanted that arrow
towards the vertex,
which means towards the variable,
which means negative, I guess,
then you put it here,
and that will simulate
putting it to the actual x.
So how does this duplicator work?
We're going to see a couple of them,
but this is a simple implication chain.
So if you say, okay, what is--
Let's just expand out, what is c_x?
It has x in its positive form
and x' in its negative form.
So it's 2SAT clause,
it's x or not x',
which we can rewrite as x' implies x.
And c'_x here is the opposite,
so it's x' in its positive form
and x in its negative form,
which you can rewrite
as x implies x'.
So x implies x', x' implies x.
This is the same--
together this is saying x if and
only if x', or they're equal.
So we've successfully copied to here.
We just apply that same gadget here,
and great!
And notice we're just putting clauses on
clause lines, variables on variable lines.
And this whole gadget basically lives
in a thickened version of this edge.
And so if the original structure is
planar,
we're not going to add any crossings here,
we're just resolving crossings
with the vertical lines,
assuming the original drawing
has no vertical lines and stuff like that.
All right. So that's the main gadget.
Now let's put that together
in an actual example.
So here we have planar monotone 3SAT.
We have all the variables
on a horizontal line.
We have some--
Oh, I guess we're not assuming
monotone here, but we could have.
We have some clauses above,
some clauses below,
and then we just plug
that gadget in a whole bunch.
So the main thing that's happening is,
because a variable was occupying
an interval of the x axis here, we're just
making-- let's say this is the variable,
we're making many copies of it
through that horizontal bar,
and then we're also copying it
to where it's needed in a clause.
So here, for example, is the top clause,
which is the OR of this variable,
this variable, and this variable.
And if you say look at v_1,
it's kind of stretched here
but this thing here
is exactly the copy gadget.
So this gets copied
here, gets copied here, to here, to here,
up to here.
And then this is the actual clause that
brings together three variables in whatever
signs you were supposed to have
according to the input instance.
So it's an ugly drawing, but it's planar.
It resolved all the crossings
with the vertical lines. All's good.
Okay, so that's linked planar 3SAT.
It's hard.
I think there are
some variables that are getting
used four times here,
so we don't have 3SAT-3 yet.
It's not sided, it's not monotone, but
it's a good start.
So let me show you
some of the other versions.
Here is the version where every clause
is monotone, all positive or all negative.
This is-- In this notation
that means that for every clause,
all the edges are incoming or
all the edges are outgoing.
This previous gadget here
did not satisfy that.
With the added clauses
we had one incoming and one outgoing.
So we're going to
change the copy gadget into
a different one that also works.
So I guess we're illustrating it here.
So here's x, we're not going to make a
copy, that's tricky.
We're going to negate the variable.
So x-bar will be the negation of x.
So x-bar is just a label,
whereas this symbol (¬) means
boolean negation.
So we have two clauses here,
one is all positive, one is all negative.
So this one is all positive.
It's hard to get the parity right here.
So it says x or x-bar,
which we can rewrite as say
not x implies x-bar. And the other one
is the same, but with negation,
so we have not x or not x-bar.
This is, we can rewrite as
x implies not x-bar.
So on the other hand,
if x is true, x-bar must be false,
if x is false, x-bar must be true.
So this guarantees that x and x-bar
are not equal.
And so we do exactly the same proof,
but scaled up
by a factor of two horizontally,
because now we're going to alternate,
you see, there's two different types
of vertical dashed lines:
there's the positive ones
and the negative ones.
We want to make sure we never want
to use these negated variables
because we didn't need them.
But if we do it twice,
this is an actual copy of x.
And so as long as we only use
the variables from the thick dashed lines,
we have essentially
the same old proof as before.
But now these added clauses are monotone,
they're all in or all out.
And as long as we're reducing now
from monotone planar 3SAT,
then these clauses will also be monotone
and so whole thing is monotone.
Great.
Okay.
This, this gad-- clause--
Sorry. This picture here uses a variable
four times.
If you mess around with this gadget
some more, split it up into more pieces,
make these two 4-cycles bigger,
you can get it down
to at most three occurrences.
But I don't think it's super exciting,
so I won't talk about it here
anymore.
All right, let's do sided.
This is going to use-- this is maybe
at a high level, but it's a similar idea.
So we have our
clauses here, which--
So we have our c_x and c_x' from before.
This one is all positive
and this one is all negative.
But instead of them being attached
to the same two variables,
we're stretching them out
with an implication chain.
So this, this clause
just says this variable implies this one,
this one says this one implies that one,
and that turns out to do the same thing.
So all these top variables
will be positive copies
of x and the bottom variables--
They'll be equal to each other,
and all the ones down here
will be negated versions of that.
So using the same
4-cycle as before,
but stretching it out more,
we get a bunch of positive copies
on the top and then you just connect them.
You use that duplicator
to connect things to a clause.
Here's an actual clause
that has some stuff incoming and outgoing.
If this was a monotone
3SAT instance initially,
then these arrows will be incoming on
on the left side
and outgoing on the right side
because all the positive edges
are on one side and negative edges
on the other side.
And this splitter has the property
that all the edges go to the right.
And so it also has the feature
that it alternates
between, uh, positive and negative edges,
because if you go
to a white circle, that's negative;
if you go to a black circle,
that's positive.
And so they alternate.
Maybe
you have to remember from the spiral,
this is inside--
this is inside the cycle, outside, inside,
outside, inside, outside.
The columns alternate.
So that gives you sidedness.
Messy diagrams.
Even messier is if you want exactly
three variables per clause.
I don't claim to have
fully grokked this one.
But with some complicated gadget,
you can make it work.
So that is why linked planar 3SAT is hard,
and why most of these variants are hard.
Now we're going to go back to Mario
and try to apply--
try to come up with a reduction from
sided planar-- linked planar 3SAT
to Super Mario Brothers.
So we have two parts:
variable gadgets and clause gadgets.
Hopefully we don't have any
crossover gadgets anymore.
So the variable gadgets turn out to be
easy using our existing gadgets.
So let's focus in on a variable.
So we're reducing from this sided
linked planar 3SAT.
We're zooming in on a variable.
We can implement a variable,
it just needs to choose--
So there's this path
that Mario is going to follow,
visiting the variables in order,
and so it comes in from the
previous variable on the path,
and then Mario is going to do
a similar long fall thing,
it can-- he can choose false or true, then
visit all the corresponding clauses,
and then recombine
and go to the next variable.
So this is also
we use long falls to make this happen,
like in the original variable gadget,
it's just sort of a little shifted
from how we drew it before.
We do want to make sure
that Mario can't come in here
and then go and visit
the true side as well,
but that's easy to do with long falls.
This is good.
But here I want to point out
we're using sidedness because
we want all the connections--
So there's the path here,
we want all the false connections
to be on one side
and all the true connections
to be on the other side.
It's not enough to just be planar.
If there were false--
if there was a false connection here
and then a true connection,
and then a false connection
all on the same side,
that would be super bad for planarity
because you have to go from here...
If you chose false,
you have to go to the false connection,
come back, somehow avoid
crossing the true connection,
and then go to the next false connection.
So-- But if we're sided, we know
they're all on one side or the other,
and so we can wire this thing up in this
nice planar way.
Okay, so we really need sidedness
for variables to work.
Unfortunately,
clauses want some other property, so--
Well, it's not so bad.
So for each clause up here,
what we want is when we're visiting
the clause path, the solid lines,
we're checking all the clauses.
So there's one check line
through the middle of the gadget here
that's going to be traversable
if there's a star for Mario
to get through the fire bars.
And we need three
different ways to unlock this gadget.
And as I said before,
we can't assume that all three of these
are on one side of the red line,
there's going to have to be
some on each side.
We can assume that there's
at most two connections on each side.
So that's where I'm going to use this
maybe, it's a little nicer.
But there's here, for example,
two on the left, one on the right,
we can't avoid that.
This is annoying because
if you look at our Mario proof,
it kind of needed-- really wanted Mario
to be all on one side of the line.
The check line is basically this
horizontal line here
that's really coming from here
and going through all this stuff.
That's the check line
through the middle of the gadget.
And here we have Mario coming
and initiating stars from one side.
So we can't do this with the construction
we have so far.
One way to make this work
is to just build a
slightly more complicated gadget
where you also have
some stars that launch from the top.
And if you arrange this geometry right,
these stars will hop down into this
nice area.
This is probably not--
it's not too bad to make this work,
but it's kind of annoying and tedious.
So I'd like to avoid making the Mario
clause gadget any more complicated.
This would work,
but it turns out there's an easier way,
just using linked planar 3SAT
and this gadget,
which is--
We're going to take this idea
from the variable gadget --
which is to split Mario into two halves
according to a binary choice,
and merge those paths back together
-- also in the clause.
I'm going to take this
clause and modify it.
Boom.
So we're going to split it.
We're going to have a choice at the top,
Mario can choose to go left or right
when verifying this clause.
The idea is this clause
is true-- is satisfied
if either the left side satisfies it
or the right side satisfies it.
So we just need one
out of the three variables to satisfy it.
So let's just do this choice,
merge back together at the end, and Mario
will be able to get from here to here
if and only if either the left side
or the right side is satisfied.
The left side satisfied if this or this
star gets onto this gadget.
So the idea is this gadget here
is the regular Mario clause gadget.
All of the enablers are from one side.
So all of the question
blocks would be here,
so you tilt your head this way,
so this way is up.
And this gadget, you tilt your head
so this way is up,
and all of the question blocks
that make stars come from one side.
So a very simple little fix.
We already needed these choice
and merge gadgets for the variable,
we can re-use them for the clause.
And now sidedness is enough to give us
what we want.
Sidedness plus monotonicity
also would have been enough,
but that's not hard,
so we can't do that.
Cool.
I think now I want to show you a different
way to think about the same thing.
Let's check, yeah.
Which is a slightly stronger
form of linked planar 3SAT.
That's a little-- It's
going to use the same--
It's going to build this same idea,
but do it in a completely 3SAT context
instead of talking about
choices and merges,
that's a little bit Mario specific
(or platform game specific),
and it's just going to say
something about formulas.
So this is a new result,
and a new name,
which I made up.
So I've said n times
that sided linked
monotone 3SAT is not hard.
But if you add “inter” to this thing
-- interlinked planar
monotone 3SAT, sided, is hard.
So I just need to define what that is.
So we're going to take monotone
3SAT -- also works with 3SAT-3 --
and it's going to be NP-hard
Seems like I'm repeating a lot,
and I am, but the
cycle
is going to be a little bit different.
(And it would help
if I put the words in the right order.)
Variable-clause bipartite graph, as usual.
And now we're going to add a cycle
that visits all variables and clauses.
Okay.
But before we said
there was a cycle, that visits all
variables and _then_ visits all clauses.
Now I'm just going to say there's a cycle
that visits all the variables
and clauses, but intermixed,
but not in any order,
in a nice order.
Each clause is after
it's three variables.
So this is what we want for Mario, right?
We don't actually care
that all the variables are set before
all the clauses are checked.
We just need that whenever we're checking
a clause, we should be able to check it,
meaning all the variables--
all its variables
better have been assigned already.
So in this proof we'd be totally fine with
mixing the dashed
and the solid lines a little bit,
as long as whatever we're verifying here,
these variables
have already been set,
so we will be able to pass through
if at least one of them has been set, then
one of the literals has been set to true.
I should say, finish my sentence.
The bipartite graph
plus the cycle is planar.
Okay.
Even sided.
So this problem remains hard even with
the sided constraint, which is this one.
The positive and negative edges
are on opposite sides of now this cycle.
Okay, so this is the best of both worlds,
where we have monotonicity,
we have sidedness,
just our cycle got a little weaker,
but at least for this application
it's strong enough.
And I have a picture of how to prove it.
It's actually really the same proof that
we just saw, but done in a formula context.
So this is a slightly bigger picture
just to show how it will work in general.
This is a 4SAT clause.
It has two positive versions above, two
negative versions below, let's say.
And because this is--
we're reducing from sided
linked planar 3SAT, not monotone.
So this clause is not monotone,
but it is sided:
all the positive edges are on one side,
all the negative edges are on the other.
And what we're going to do
is add a new variable here
that's going to represent is this clause
satisfied from above or below?
Could be satisfied by both,
then this variable
will have multiple choices.
But when it's... let's see...
So the-- it's, I think, easier
to think-- look in the clauses here.
But the first thing is to observe
in this picture that now--
It's still sided:
all the positive edges are above this
horizontal line,
all the negative are below.
But in addition,
this clause, all the arrows are out,
this clause, all the arrows are in,
because we split this guy
into two clauses.
And now if we look at the formula view,
I think it's a little easier.
We have a or b or x on the top and we have
not x or not c or not d on the bottom.
So the idea is if x is true,
this get satisfied for free,
but this doesn't get any benefit,
and so one of these two better be true,
which would have satisfied this clause.
If x is false,
this get satisfied for free,
but this gets eliminated,
and so we get a or b.
So either a or b or not c or not d
must be set true for this to be true,
just like over here.
Okay, so we've got a reduction from sided
linked to sided interlinked monotone.
Really using the same idea,
but instead of doing the choice
and merge at the--
in the Mario context,
we're doing it at the formula level.
But the other thing to notice is,
so all these variables
will be set early
bef-- from-- In this reduction,
all of these will get visited
before all the clauses.
We're adding this variable,
but assuming this arrow goes to the right,
this variable gets set
before the clauses that need it check it.
If the arrow went to the left,
you reflect this diagram.
Cool.
So that's two ways
to use sided linked planar
3SAT in a nice way,
and I want to give you a third way
to look at this proof,
which is going to try to abstract--
So for this construction to work,
we needed three different gadgets.
We needed a choice for Mario,
we needed a merge for Mario,
and we needed this unlock structure
where there are two different ways
to unlock the same path.
I'd like to formalize that and simplify it
a little bit into something called
the Opening Doors Framework.
So let me write a theorem first,
then we'll see it applied to
the Mario setup.
So I'm going to use this term
and not define it precisely.
It will be defined
precisely in a few weeks
when we talk about a general gadget
framework, but I'm going to
just refer to it informally
as planar motion planning.
This is going to be a problem
where I have a bunch of gadgets
and I have a player,
an agent that is running around
a network of those gadgets,
and that network is a planar graph,
just like essentially
these kinds of drawings,
and each of these dots
is going to be a little gadget.
And now I'm going to tell you
what those gadgets can do.
So one thing you're allowed to do
is build branching hallways.
These we can think of
as just a vertex,
where Mario can go one of three ways.
It can come in one edge,
leave on any of these edges.
This is sort of something
we always take for granted,
and I'll kind of omit this in the future,
but it is something we need
the ability for Mario to do.
The interesting part, this is the--
Okay, another thing we need
is called a one-way mechanism.
There are few different choices
what this could be.
Simplest one is a diode, which
I'm going to-- Probably I'll actually draw
all of these as a box with an arrow on it.
So the idea is you can come in
from the left and leave on the right,
but you can't go
from the right to the left.
In a diode, you could go many times
left to right, never right to left.
This is long falls.
Long falls in many video games,
platform games with gravity
give you a diode.
You can fall one way,
you can't fall up.
There are many other versions
that suffice.
I'm going to mention two of them.
One is a directed crumbler.
Maybe I'll draw that as a dotted line
or dashed line,
I don't know.
This is an edge that you can use
only one time left to right.
You walk left to right,
and then it crumbles away,
and you can't use it in any direction.
You can never go right to left,
you can go left to right once.
That also works fine for this proof.
Slightly more generally,
you can use what we'll call
a no-return gadget.
This is actually a family of gadgets
that includes these too.
But the key idea is
we can allow
right to left traversal
before we do a left to right traversal.
The point of no-return
is that once you go through left to right,
you can't return right to left.
But before you go left to right,
maybe you could go right to left.
So sometimes this is easier,
you can't avoid this.
I'm not going to justify the
no-return here.
Mostly we're just going to be thinking
about diodes and directed crumblers.
But the theorem I'm about to say
is also true in this setting.
And then finally,
we get to opening doors.
[STUDENT] Is it important that
the crumbler is directed?
Is important that the crumbler
is directed...
I don't know.
You tell me.
I thought it was.
[STUDENT] If you go through it,
you can't go the other way,
[STUDENT]
so it satisfies no-return property.
Oh, I see.
Good.
That's true.
Okay.
Directed crumbler is right,
but also undirected crumbler is right.
So what's an undirected crumbler?
It's just a dash line with no arrow.
So this one, you can go left to right
and it disappears,
or you can go right to left
and it disappears.
But in particular, if you first go left
to right, you can't go back right to left,
so that's also a no-return gadget,
so also good.
So any of those things.
No-return is really the family
that includes
all those great one-way mechanisms.
We need this for
choices and merges
wherever we were using long falls before.
Now, what about the gadget
that does this unlock mechanism?
This I'm going to call an
Opening Door with Two Buttons,
which I will draw like this.
Let's draw this as a dotted line
to the right
and maybe a wiggly line here.
So there are two
open ports,
open buttons on the bottom of this gadget,
and there's this dotted line,
which is not possible to traverse.
If agent comes in here,
you're not able to get here
unless this path has been opened
by one of these two buttons.
This is like in Mario,
there's two question blocks here.
If you hit them,
you put a star on this path
and then you're able to traverse the
fire bars, but not otherwise.
Okay.
There's two versions of this gadget.
It could be directed
to put an arrow here
or it could be undirected,
which is traversing left or right
is the same as traversing right to left,
only possible if you open the door.
Cool.
So that's the end of the theorem
statement.
Planar motion planning is NP-hard if you
have three gadgets: branching hallways,
one of these one-way mechanisms
(aka no-return gadget),
and an opening door with two buttons.
It may seem like this is not simpler,
but this is a way to encapsulate
what's going on in that proof over there,
without building explicit choice and merge.
It turns out you can build
choice and merge using these gadgets.
So this is the
sense in which it's simpler.
If you want to
build a choice that's like a branching
hallway
combined with a couple of long falls
or one way mechanisms.
So if we assume
we're only coming from here
and once we traverse
one of these choices, we can't immediately
go back by the no-return property.
And so we've chosen, say, true or false
using-- we've built it
using branching hallways here
and one way mechanisms.
Similarly merge is
this picture.
And here I'm assuming
I have a diode or a directed crumbler.
I'm not going to handle the other cases,
but it's possible
with a bunch of case analysis.
So if we assume these only work
in one direction top down,
if I come through here,
I won't be able to go up the other path,
all I can do is come out this way.
So that's how--
You plug these two gadgets
into what was going on here,
and we've reduced the number of gadgets
by one.
I added branching hallways, but
we were using branching hallways already.
And instead of having a separate choice
and merge gadget,
we now just have the one-way mechanism
that was enough to build choice and merge.
We still need this red thing
and I'm going to redraw this picture.
So stare at the picture for a second
and we transition to--
This is our new kind of reduction
from sided linked planar 3SAT.
But now using these one-way mechanisms,
branching hallways, [and opening doors].
So this was this the choice and merge,
I've just inlined here,
and in this case we need a choice
we don't actually need a merge
because we just need this to satisfy
one way or the other.
Not a big deal.
Then we just have
a branching hallway
to go to the next clause.
And so all we need
are these little green boxes.
There's two of them.
Well, there's also this purple dot.
But other than branching hallways,
we have the one way mechanism,
we have the opening door with two buttons.
As long as you can build those two
two, this NP-hardness framework
tells you your problem is NP-hard.
So let's apply it to some things.
Oh, I have one last thing to mention,
which is opening door
two buttons is pretty good.
What about one button?
That sadly is an open problem,
but if you have crossovers, opening doors
with one button is hard.
And the open problem
is in this planar setting
(we have no crossings among how
these gadgets are connected)
opening doors with one button.
Maybe it isn't hard.
So the-- We need--
We seem to need two buttons so far.
Okay, so let's look at some proofs.
This is the Mario proof,
or the gadgets in the Mario proof.
We had variable, clause, and crossover.
We can now simplify by saying, okay,
we don't need crossover,
because linked planar 3SAT
gives it to us provided we have a one-way,
which is a long fall,
and we have a two button opening door.
So I get to remove one of these
question blocks, get it slightly smaller.
Two question blocks is enough
for, you know, one side of this reduction.
So now two slightly smaller diagrams
instead of three, especially avoiding
this really complicated diagram,
we get that Mario is NP-hard.
In fact, in some sense, you can get away
with one gadget because this
two button opening door contains
inside it a directed crumbler.
If I just erase the left part
here and erase this wall,
then Mario coming over here
can gain a star
and go through this edge once,
and never again.
You never go right to left,
and there's only one star here,
so once you get the star, you can go left
to right, and you get a directed crumbler.
So this gadget alone,
if you just sort of wire
these together, gives us
the directed crumbler
because this is a directed opening door.
So that's kind of nice.
So almost one figure
is enough to prove Mario is hard.
There-- In our original paper
that did the Mario proof, we also analyzed
a bunch of other games like
Legend of Zelda: Link to the Past.
So this in particular with this hookshot
mechanism that you just saw
illustrated here where you can hook
to a close enough object,
and some of the objects are movable,
you can push them around.
So we had a proof, they had a variable,
a clause and a crossover.
These weren't particularly difficult,
but I'd like to simplify this proof.
The main one is the clause where you can--
if you come and satisfy this clause,
you can push this block down one
and then you'll be able to hookshot
from the left to the right, say,
if any of these are pushed down.
So now we can simplify this proof.
We only need two out of three
of these blocks.
We don't need the crossover.
And we really just need a
one-way out of here,
not this whole variable
construction. So proof gets simpler.
Another Nintendo
video game we analyzed is Metroid.
Ooh, get some music too.
And this proof had a really complicated
crossover using some fancy
timing with these little monsters
that climb around,
and then a pretty simple clause,
which is if Metroid--
if Samus can get to one of these
three places, then you can shoot
all of the enemies so that later
when you're coming here, rolling around
(and you don't have bombs in this level,
so you can't destroy the enemies in any
other way), you have to roll through
over here, only possible
if you destroyed the all the enemies.
So now we can thankfully throw away
that crossover and slightly reduce
from three buttons to two buttons.
Next one is Donkey Kong Country.
Here is a hardness proof where
Donkey Kong can come through here
and grab a barrel and throw this barrel,
it will roll and kill this bee.
And as long as you can get
to one of these three spots,
you can throw the barrel and kill the bee.
And later to check this clause, Donkey
Kong comes in here
and gets fired through the bee
with no control.
And so you'll-- and will end up
way over here at the next clause.
And that'll be possible
only if you satisfied the clause.
The reason I'm saying all that is
we don't want Donkey Kong to be able
to just come down here and satisfy
the clause or, you know, continue
the checking path of all the clauses.
It's really important, if Donkey comes
down here, can't do anything.
And as long as you
put the next clause
far enough away to the right, that's true.
Okay. There's also a crossover.
We don't need that anymore.
All right.
Last Nintendo proof
I'm going to talk about is Pokémon.
This is the core construction
for the people who know Pokémon very well.
We're going to build
two kinds of trainers.
Trainers are people
you battle Pokémon with, in the game.
We're going to have weak trainers
where the player always wins
and strong trainers
where the player always loses
for this reduction.
This details
how you do that in the various
generations of Pokémon.
And so the red characters
here are the weak trainers,
the blue ones are the strong trainers.
And the way trainers work--
Let's look at the variable gadget.
Simple example. So this is a trainer.
Trainers have a field of vision
in front of them.
It's like a column or a row.
And if you walk-- if the
player walks here,
the trainer-- into this field of vision,
they're sort of detected
and the trainer will walk towards you
until they're one space away from you
and then fight you.
And in the red case, you'll win,
and then the trainer
is permanently in that position
and never fights again.
And-- Or if you decide
to talk to the trainer from the side,
then you'll fight them immediately.
In this case, you win,
and then the trainer will be permanently
in its original position.
So you get to choose
whether they move to you
or if you can talk to them from the side.
So this gives you a variable,
because if I come here
and the trainer moves down one square,
then I'll never be able to get to the true
path,
I'll only be able to get to the false
path.
And conversely,
if I come and talk to the trainer
and fix them in their location,
then I come here,
I'll be able to get to true,
but I'll never be able to get to false.
So this is not a one-way,
but it's
a variable, which is what we need.
There's a very complicated crossover
and then there's a clause
which is pretty simple.
The idea is
if you haven't satisfied the clause
and you walk across here, these trainers
will each move down one square,
and then if you go up here,
this trainer will come
and attack you and you lose.
But if at least one of the literals
is satisfied, you can freeze one of these
red guys in place and then this guy
won't be able to see you.
That's part of the rules I didn't mention.
But then you'll be able to get through.
Okay, so we can throw away this crossover
and reduce the opening door
to two buttons.
We don't have a one way mechanism here,
but we have a variable
and that turns out to work
basically just as well,
where instead of--
We used to have that if you did x,
you visit all the clauses that include x
and then you route to the next variable.
That that doesn't work
because we don't have a way to do this
merging without leakage.
And so instead what we do is just link
all the variables directly together,
which is exactly what we get out of
linked 3SAT and each one has a choice
and then is connected
to the set of clauses
for the true or for the false.
So basically the the variables
are connected to each other over here
instead of being connected
to each other after the choice,
which is not what
you want to do with long falls,
but it's what you want to do
with this kind of
variable gadget.
Okay, cool.
One more topic
-- unless there are questions --
which is closing doors.
So we have this nice opening door
framework.
You might naturally ask,
what about closing door framework?
And there is such a thing,
and it also
really likes to use linked planar 3SAT.
So this theorem has a similar structure
to the opening doors framework.
Planar motion planning,
this is problem of given
a planar network of gadgets
that I'm about to specify,
a planar graph of them,
and you have some start location,
some end location,
can I get from A to B, that's going to be
NP-hard provided we have two gadgets.
One is branching hallway,
just like before.
In this theorem
we don't even need a one-way mechanism.
We just need what I'm going to call
a Distant Closing.
This is a gadget
that has two paths,
two ways to traverse it,
and at least one
fully closes the other.
And it could also close itself,
we don't care.
Okay.
I'm going to give you two examples
of this gadget,
just to give some intuition.
And these are
the ones that tend to come up the most.
One is a NAND.
So this is-- I have
two paths and
one of them closes the other.
Sorry, each of them closes the other.
So if I traverse this path,
this top edge,
then the other one closes,
and if I traverse the bottom edge,
the other one closes.
So you can't use both of them.
So it's NAND.
Another one is
called matched crumbles.
This is the return of the crumbler,
but in a fancier version.
So here I have again two paths,
but they're dashed paths
and they also close each other.
So just like the original crumbler
which had one one edge that disappears.
Now if I traverse this one,
they both disappear,
so they're matched to be
in the same [state].
So if I traverse the top one,
they both crumble.
If I traverse the bottom one,
These are two examples of distant closing.
There are others, but these turn out
to be sort of the core ones.
And there is another constraint,
which is
this gadget needs to be
in one of the following geometries.
So there are bunch of cases.
This is what we call antiparallel.
This is what we call crossing.
And the other one
you might imagine is parallel.
This one, we forbid,
it's an open problem
whether this works,
but let's say it doesn't work.
Where we know it works
is if we have directed edges
(so if each of the paths is directed)
and they're in opposite directions
when you draw them in the plane,
or if they cross each other,
those are both good.
We don't know how to handle
when both the edges
are parallel to each other.
Or if the edges are undirected,
there's only two cases:
they could either be
non-crossing or crossing those both work.
Or they could be mixed,
maybe one edge is directed
and the other one is undirected,
that's also okay,
you can have it like this,
you can have it like this.
There's no distinction between parallel
and antiparallel
when there's only one directed edge.
So these are all good.
We really just need to forbid
this one case.
And what I'm going to show you is a proof
that closing doors is hard
via reduction from
linked-- sided linked planar 3SAT,
our good friend.
And I hand-drew this
but I think it's
a little tedious to draw on the board
so I'm just going to show my hand-drawing.
So here is the setup.
I need to write an assumption for this
to make sense.
So proof.
So there are many possible
distant closing gadgets.
I'm going to assume
that I have some of them, and then later,
we'll see how to convert other
gadgets into these ones.
Okay, so I'm
going to assume that I have a parallel
(or a non-crossing [if undirected/mixed])
and a crossing set-up.
So that was, say,
this one which we don't actually--
isn't enough for hardness.
But I assume I have this one
and this one or these two or these two.
And it can be
a NAND or it can be matched crumblers.
I don't want to think
about the other cases right now.
Just these two.
Then we'll handle the other cases.
So when I draw one of these boxes
is either a NAND or a matched crumblers.
So whenever I traverse one of these edges,
the other one falls.
Maybe the one I just traversed
also closes behind itself,
I don't care.
So here is how
we build sided linked planar 3SAT.
For a variable,
we come in, we want to do a choice.
So we're just going to have
a branching hallway,
and then we're going
to have one of these gadgets.
And if I take the top path, I prevent
myself from later taking the bottom path.
So great. Then I visit all the clauses
with the appropriate assignment
of literal,
either the negation or as true form.
And then to do the merge,
I do the same thing.
I'm going to have one of these gadgets.
So if I traverse here,
I won't be able to go backwards and visit
the clauses with the other assignment.
So great. I built a variable
using this choice/merge idea.
Then I'm going to build a clause.
This is where it gets interesting,
and this is where we're going to use
just one crossing gadget.
But we need it.
We're going to use it essentially
as a crossover here in a limited form.
The point is
we never need to use both of these paths.
What are these paths where we want to do
a branching hallway here and either--
This clause is satisfied by
x_1 or x_2 or not x_3.
If this is sided,
the negative versions will be on one side,
positive versions
will be on the other side.
Again, we're using
that there's only two connections above
and at most two connections below.
There's only at most
three connections total.
So let's say there's two on top,
one on the bottom at most.
And so either--
So there's a bit of a catch here.
Notice
here I wrote when the variable is true,
I go and visit all the clauses with not x.
This is the opposite of what we had
with opening doors,
because here we're closing doors.
So if I visited a clause with--
Say, I set x_1 to false here,
which would not satisfy this clause,
then I would go and visit this clause,
and when I visit it,
I walk this path which closes this one,
which means I can't satisfy the clause
by following this route.
So I need to be able to satisfy
this clause with one of these three boxes.
If they're all closed, I'm screwed.
If at least one of them is open,
let's say this one is open,
then I can find a path
that goes there and get to the check out,
and then go to the next
clause and check that one.
And so here we're really just
using this as a way
to get from here to here or from here
over to here without any leakage.
And it's actually the parallel ones
that are doing
most of the work of like making sure
the choices are a satisfying assignment.
And we're using this as a crossover
to make it planar.
Okay, so that works great,
if we have a NAND
or we have matched dicrumblers,
and if we have both the parallel version
and the crossing version.
But luckily we can reduce to those cases
all the time.
It's just a little bit of case
analysis and reductions.
So the first reduction I want to do
is if I have a distant closing gadget,
any of them, I can make a NAND
or a matched crumblers.
It's funny pluralism there.
This is a gadget called "matched crumblers"
because there's two crumblers in the gadget.
So this is a generic thing
we're going to do.
Suppose we have some gadget.
I'm going to draw it as antiparallel
and then something happens here.
Let's say,
for example, if I traverse the top edge,
it closes the bottom edge.
But traversing the bottom edge does
nothing.
Just as an example.
I'm going to take that gadget,
rotate it 180 degrees for this diagram.
So the arrows actually look the same.
But now-- like the big solid arrows.
But now traversing this bottom
edge closes the top edge.
And then I'm
just going to wire these together.
And then this is
my big gadget.
It again has two different ways
to traverse it.
If you traverse the top one, what happens?
This one gets closed
and here nothing happens.
But then if I tried to come and
traverse it the other way,
I won't be able to because I'll
get stuck here because this was closed.
Similarly, if I traverse the bottom edge,
this one closes
and then nothing happens here.
But if I try to then traverse it
the other way, I get stuck.
So what I got was, before
this original gadget
I was given only closed from one side,
only one of the traversals closed
the other one.
But when I take two of them, then either
traversal closes both.
And now there are a few cases here.
Maybe also when you traverse this edge
it closed itself,
in that case we get matched crumblers,
because this one will have closed itself
and this one will have closed itself.
Or if it doesn't close itself,
we would have gotten a NAND.
So with one picture,
if I-- in the antiparallel case,
I convert any distant
closing
gadget to a NAND or a matched crumblers.
If I have--
This also works in the undirected case
if there are no arrows here.
But if I have crossing
(with or without directions)
this is slightly more annoying.
If I wire it in the same way
I convert a crossing gadget
into a parallel gadget which I don't like.
So there are multiple ways to do this,
but I think the simplest one to me
is to just put a third one.
Now it's crossing again.
And one of these is rotated 180--
[incorrect]
or maybe you don't even-- Yeah, probably
one of these should be rotated 180,
so that if, say,
this one is controlling that,
this one will control that.
And so I got confused here.
So if I follow this path and, say,
say, following this path closes this one,
I want following this path
to also close this one,
which actually is--
maybe you don't even flip,
I think.
Right. I'll call this path 1, path 2.
This is path 1.
This is path 2.
And they alternate.
And so if I already have, let's say,
this dotted arrow is going up.
So if I follow path 1, I close path 2,
and I want also that
if I follow path 2,
I close path 1 and that works
if these gadgets are actually
the same gadget with no rotation.
Cool.
Okay, so this is great.
I've reduced to
this part, NAND or matched crumblers.
And this is no constraint,
directed or undirected or mixed,
that's all the things.
The remaining part is this.
I would like to have
parallel and crossing,
but maybe-- and I know I'm not allowed
to have started with parallel.
But I could have
started with antiparallel,
that's neither of these things.
Or I could have started with undirected
non -rossing,
also neither of these things. Or even
I could have started with crossing.
That doesn't give me parallel,
I wanted both. Luckily,
none of these are very hard
[to prove NP-hard].
Let's see, the simplest one is
crossing to parallel.
This is the same construction again.
We just saw how to do that,
if I only use two copies.
Now, I'm assuming these are
NANDs or matched crumblers.
So if I traverse this one, it crumbles
or it destroys the other and vice versa.
So, you know, great.
I turned to crossing into parallel.
That's not very hard.
More interesting is
antiparallel to crossing.
And this will give you a feel
for why antiparallel is so cool.
I think this is where I use a reflection.
Okay.
So these are both antiparallel gadgets.
This one is a reflection of that one.
So we're assuming
if you can build a gadget,
you can also build its reflection.
So if I come in here and traverse
this edge, I destroy the other one
and now I can't go this way because of
the arrow's in the wrong direction,
and I can't go this way
because I destroyed that edge,
so the only place I can go is out here,
and then I also destroy this edge.
And it's symmetric.
So you get a crossing
and it-- if you do
one of those traversals,
it destroys the other. Cool.
Side note: you can also go
from crossing to antiparallel.
But that's not something we need for this
because we just wanted
parallel and crossing.
So either we start with crossing
then we can convert it to parallel,
or we start with antiparallel,
then we convert it to crossing
and we convert that to parallel
and we get all the gadgets we want.
There is one case left which is
undirected non-crossing to crossing.
So for this construction to work
I really needed this arrow.
If I don't have arrows in my gadget,
everything is undirected.
I claim undirected
non-crossing is still good, but
I definitely can't use this construction.
So we are going to use
a different construction.
Try drawing this another way.
And symmetrify...
Okay, so these are gadgets,
these big boxes.
If I traverse this edge,
it destroys the other one and vice versa
and maybe itself.
That's the NAND or the matched crumblers.
So if I come in here,
then I destroy this path,
then I have to go here,
I follow this edge,
I destroy this path.
Now I have this branching hallway.
I can't go this way, cause
that's destroyed.
I could try to go this way,
but I get stuck, cause this is destroyed.
So in fact, I have to go this way
and destroy this edge, and then come
over here, destroy that edge.
I've completely obliterated
the other traversal path,
but I made it across
starting from an undirected
non-crossing thing.
And I get an undirected crossing.
Oh, I forgot to mention this proof
if I drew lots of arrows, but it works--
I wasn't assuming any of the arrows.
I kept arguing,
even if I come here,
I won't be able to go back this way.
I wasn't trying to respect the arrows,
so this proof works for the directed case
or the undirected case [or mixed],
as long as you have parallel
and crossing versions of your gadget.
Great.
So that is the
closing doors framework.
Let's just see how it works
in a few examples.
So one of them is a proof that we saw
a couple lectures ago in the SAT lecture.
This-- I'm just-- I'm not going to remind you
how this proof works, I'm just going to say
we proved Push-1 and PushPush-1
was NP-hard with a whole bunch of gadgets.
This isn't-- this is only
like half of them.
I am not even showing the crossover.
But I want to show
that one of the gadgets here
that we were using just as like
a little piece in this construction
is this gadget.
I called it "block other" in the lecture.
Now, I would call it a parallel NAND,
because if you go from northeast,
it blocks the other one.
You can't do that traversal.
So this is a directed parallel NAND.
Sadly, we don't know hardness
for that case.
But luckily there's a whole bunch
of Push hardness proofs.
And so I'm just going to show you
another one which used to be covered
in this class, called Push-1X,
so reduction from 3-coloring.
Push-1X is where
after you traverse a square, it crumbles,
you can't traverse that square again.
It's interesting because it's
in NP, It turns out it's still NP-hard
-- big, complicated proof,
this is less than half of it.
But one of those gadgets
here is a NAND gadget
and lo and behold, it's
almost the same as the previous one.
This one is antiparallel.
I'm going to zoom into that
and show you how it works.
So this is the gadget and I'm showing the
two possible traversals on the right.
And you can see that
they are antiparallel to each other.
But it's the same idea if I come and push
one of the blocks, then I'm unable
to push the other one from either side
because I only have strength 1.
So great.
This one gadget, plus branching
hallways, proves
that Push-1 is NP-hard,
Push-1X is NP-hard,
PushPush-1 is NP-hard
and PushPush-1X is NP-hard,
because PushPush will behave exactly
the same here.
Very simple proof, very cool
application of ultimately sided
linked planar 3SAT.
Zelda also has blocks
that you can push once.
Here's a little piece of the level.
A lot of Zelda games have this
where you can push blocks only once.
Same proof works
because it only involves pushing blocks
once, whereas the previous proofs
involved pushing multiple times.
Here's another pushing blocks
game called Push-1G,
where the blocks experience gravity,
but you don't, the player doesn't.
So there are bunch of gadgets here,
but in particular here
there's this thing called a NAND crossover
that is a crossing NAND by another name.
So here if you push this block,
it falls down to here,
and then you're not able to get there,
and so you have to go this way.
And similarly, if you push this one out,
it falls here, and you
have to go to there.
So great, we've got a crossing
NAND, it's NP-hard.
You don't need the other gadgets.
And finally
-- those are all simplifying proofs --
yhis is actually a new proof.
It was developed the last time we taught
this class in the problem sessions.
So this is a pulling blocks game
called "Pull?"
Here you have a choice when you approach
a block, whether you pull it--
If you walk away from the block,
you can pull it with you or you can not.
In this particular navigation,
I'm always pulling when I can.
Here, let's start from the beginning.
So I have to go this way.
I can try to get to
the bottom left, it's not possible.
So I have to go to the bottom right.
I can't get up there.
If later I try to traverse this way,
I can get started,
I won't be able to get over to the right
there,
I get stuck.
So cool.
This is a crossing NAND,
and it tells us this
pulling blocks game is NP-hard too.
Ooh, so we saw a lot of cool things.
In particular
I think the most--
we saw a very strong form of planar 3SAT
which is linked planar 3SAT and various
many strengthenings of it
that are very powerful
for proving hardness.
And then we kind of abstracted them
into two
more specific
but even easier to apply frameworks.
One is the opening doors
and the other is closing doors.
And the idea is
you just build a couple of gadgets
to do some very basic properties
and you just get NP-hardness for free.
You don't even have to mention planar
linked sided linked planar 3SAT
because we've abstracted it for you.
So you get to choose your adventure
of where--
what gadgets you build for
which kind of proof.
But this is the beginning
of a general theory of motion
planning gadgets,
which we will get to in a later lecture.
This is just a taste of all the gadgets
that are enough to prove
that your problem is hard. And that's it!