All right.
Today, we're going to talk about
the motion planning through gadgets
framework, which is a powerful framework
for understanding
how hard your game is given one or two
relatively simple gadgets.
But it's motion planning in the sense
that all these gadgets
are traversed by an agent such as Mario.
This is an example of a gadget
that we're going to try to capture
with this framework
from the very previous lecture.
Recall, this was a door
and the spiny could be on the right side
or the left side, and you can change
which side by hitting this block.
In fact, since the recording of that
previous lecture, we actually implemented
this in a hacked version
of the Super Mario Bros. ROM.
So you can see it in action
hitting the spiny
to the other side,
which lets you traverse that left path
or think it's going to show up
from the other side as well,
showing that the physics are right
and you obviously can't go through
the center because of the fire bars.
In the real gadget,
there's a block here, but this gives
you an idea of how how it all works.
So what we'd like to do
is take gadgets like this
that we can build in games
and abstract their behavior.
So, like, this gadget
is an example of a bunch of things...
a bunch of gadgets we've seen
where you have a bunch of traversable
paths that change the state of the gadget
and everything is
kind of local to the gadget.
The only thing the gadget remembers
is like the location of the spiny;
the only way it interacts
with other gadgets is from
Mario, traversing
from one place to another.
So in this case, we have two states
which we call open and closed
for the door, and there's this traverse
pathway that's possible -- this one
-- it's possible only in the open state
when the spiny is on the right.
It's not possible in this state.
If you come into this open path
and choose to hit the spiny,
you can transition by entering
at this location and leaving at this
location, transition to the open state.
So if you're in the closed state
and you follow this path,
you go to the open state in this.
If you're in the open state already,
nothing happens.
And then the other crucial one
is in order to traverse
the close line, you have to first
get the spiny to the left.
So if you're in the open state
and you do this traversal
from here to here,
you must change to the closed state.
So this is a state diagram of a gadget,
and we're going to define what/how
these can work in general.
But the idea is you draw some arrows
and on some of them
you write down a state name
and that means you go to that state
when you do that traversal.
Here's
a redrawing of the same thing, hand-drawn.
But I wanted to show two examples
from Lecture 6,
just to give a few more...
to show you a few more aspects
of these kinds of diagrams.
So one gadget was the directed
antiparallel NAND.
This was gadget with these two directed
paths in opposite directions.
That's the antiparallel aspect.
And the NAND aspect was if you traverse
the top one, the bottom one disappears.
And if you traverse
the bottom one, the top one disappears.
So you can express that
with a three-state gadget.
So one more state than the door
where when you do this
top traversal,
you go to the top state and the top state,
you still have the top traversal,
but the bottom one disappears.
And similarly, at the bottom, when you do
the bottom traversal, you go to
the bottom state which just has that arrow
and you lose the other one.
And another example from
that lecture was the undirected
noncrossing matched crumblersrs.
So this was a gadget where you could go in
either direction on each path here.
So I'm going to draw
that as a double arrow
and -- for both of the paths --
and if you do any traversal,
everything crumbles and so you're left
with no possible traversal.
So I wanted to highlight here
that when you have a bidirectional edge
like this, you write a different state
-- potentially
you could write a different state
for each arrowhead.
If I traverse this way,
I might go to one state.
I might go to another state.
In this case,
they all go to the same state.
But potentially
this could be four different states.
In addition, you could write more than one
state on one of these arrows, meaning it's
nondeterministic what happens.
You could choose to do one thing
or another.
So let's try to formalize all of that
pictures into mathematics.
So we're going to define a gadget
to consist of three things.
Q is going to be a finite set of states.
These are just labels.
L is a finite set of locations.
Which are also just labels.
So we're going to think of them
more like vertices in a graph
and then T-- oh, one thing
I want to mention
in order to express concepts
like antiparallel here,
which is meaningful only when we're
thinking about gadgets in the plane.
When we're in the plane, we need to know
not just there are four locations
here, we need to know
the order that they appear.
Let's say
a clockwise order around the gadget.
Otherwise, it's
hard to talk about things like crossings.
So for planar,
we have a cyclic ordering
of L.
And then the third thing is transitions.
Transitions we're going
to write in the form
state, comma, location, arrow,
state, comma, location.
So the meaning is,
if the gadget is in state
q, and the player enters...
the agent enters at location
a, then it's possible
to reach state r with the
agent leaving at location b.
This is a lot of words, but it's
equivalent to these kinds of diagrams.
And yeah, let me add a little more words
so we can talk about
how the agent moves around.
Probably be clearer.
So while the gadget cares about what
state it's in, in some sense, the agent
just wants to traverse the gadget.
And so we talk about a traversal
of the agent, whereas a transition
is something that happens in the gadget.
So traversal is just
defined by two locations, a and b.
You have some gadget here
and you want to know, is it possible
for the agent to get from a to b
given that the gadget is in some state.
q. So that's...
we're going to call that legal, it’s
possible
if there's some transition of the form
(q, a) → (r, b) for some state r.
And there might be more than one r.
That’s what I was saying:
you could have multiple possible states
on this transition.
We would write, for example, r
and also r prime
are different things that could happen.
Internal to the gadget.
When you do the a-to-b traversal
might be also zero,
then it's not a legal traversal and so on.
It's useful to distinguish
the deterministic case
where there's only one
such r.
It's a little bit stronger actually.
So deterministic means
that if I give you the initial state
and the location that I start at,
then there's only one thing
that can happen, both in terms of state
and in terms of location.
So if the agent goes in here,
there's only one place it can come out
and there's only one state we can reach.
So a lot of the gadgets
we'll be talking about are deterministic.
These gadgets are almost
completely deterministic,
except in some interpretation.
The open button here
in the closed state,
you could choose to take this traversal
or there's always possible
to stay in the same location
without doing
without doing any transition.
So I would call this in some sense
a nondeterministic open button.
All right.
Speaking of buttons, let me define
button.
So a button is a location
that can only be used
in a way the only valid traversal
is from it to itself.
You can never go from a to somewhere else.
You can never go from somewhere else
to a. So
in the door we have an open button,
but all the other possible traversals
in those examples are called tunnels.
A tunnel is if a and b and b...
and a-to-b
and b-to-a are the only possible
traversals involving a and b.
I should say valid here.
This is over all states.
So you can never go from a-to-c
or c-to-a or
these things.
So almost all of the
possible traversals in these
gadgets are tunnels.
These guys are paired up. It's never...
this edge might disappear
-- it's not always...
it doesn't always exist -- but it never
reconnects to some other location.
You could certainly imagine such a gadget,
but most of the gadgets we're going to
talk about today are tunnel gadgets.
Tunnel gadget means that
all of the traversals are within tunnels.
This is obviously not a tunnel gadget
because it has one button. But
yeah.
All right.
And I'll just mention for people who know
finite automata,
you can also think of a gadget
as a finite automaton
over the language of traversals.
And if you know what finite automata mean,
that will make lots of sense.
Otherwise, don't worry about it.
It's just another way
to think about the same thing.
Okay, so next
I want to define a system of gadgets.
This is where I take a bunch of gadgets.
Quite often it will be a bunch of copies
of the exact same gadget.
This is the door gadget.
Actually, it's a slightly different door
gadget
where the open button
has been replaced with an open tunnel.
So it's a three tunnel gadget;
it has open, traverse, close,
color coded here,
green, blue, and red.
The traverse line I'm going to draw dotted
if it's currently closed and solid
if it's currently open.
So you take a bunch of gadgets
and some initial state for those gadgets
like open or closed
and then you wire them together.
That's what I want to define.
Now, this is called the connection graph.
It's all the black lines in this diagram.
So let's go here.
We call this system of gadgets
or sometimes a network.
So we have a bunch of gadgets
and we have initial state for each
and we have a
connection graph
on the gadgets’ locations.
So all of these
spots are locations of
this is a six locations,
this gadget, six locations of this gadget.
Those are vertices in a graph
and we're just going to draw connections
between them.
We can also add vertices in between.
These are like the branching hallway
we mentioned in Lecture 6.
Today, we're going to basically assume
branching hallways always exist,
not worry about those.
What this is saying...
I think I have a picture here.
If we look at a connected component
of this connection graph,
this is basically a location in the system
in between the gadgets, so to speak.
So you can, for example, traverse
the gadget here
and now you're in this orange section.
You can go to any
location within that orange section,
within that connected component.
And the idea is that's freely traversable.
Doesn't change any state.
Nothing interesting happens.
You can use that
to go from gadget to gadget.
So connected components,
I'm going to call
system locations.
It's useful to think of this as a graph.
I mean, you can think of it
as just gluing together locations.
I think it's a little easier to draw
pictures when you think of it as a graph.
And it's also maybe a little clearer
to talk about...
This is supposed to be over here, sorry:
this is about the connection graph.
Connected
components are called system locations,
and we're going to call the system planar
if the gadgets plus the connection graph
are noncrossing.
I won't be super precise about that, but
I think it's pretty clear what it means.
This is not a planar system.
It's got tons of crossings.
These over unders.
So there are some places
where you can branch, like here,
and these are not those places;
these over-unders mean crossing
without the ability to traverse.
Okay so now
I want to talk about reachability.
The main problem we're interested
in solving in this kind of setup
is, we're given system,
and we're given a start location,
and we're given a goal location,
and we want to know can the agent
get from a to b, or in this case
s to t, via
some sequence of traversals
of the various gadgets in the system.
Plus you get to use connections
in the connection graph for free.
So that's a decision problem
and it's often
going to be PSPACE-complete,
but it depends what gadgets you allow.
So here's a little example.
We have this as our initial location.
This is our goal
and it's possible to do so
via this long sequence of reversals.
And if you watch closely
as this guy comes through, it,
for example, crosses
a clothesline, this edge becomes dashed.
So the gadgets are changing state
Every time you do a traversal,
you potentially change
the state of that gadget
and then you're able to still traverse
that gadget again
and this Tercel sequence,
many gadgets get traversed
a couple of times, at least in general.
It could even be exponentially many times.
And each time you interact with it,
you interact with it,
whatever the state currently is.
So here we got to the goal.
The answer is yes.
All right, so that's reachability.
The...
in some sense,
the main goal we're trying to get to
is understanding
when reachability is hard.
So let me give you
a couple of examples of such results.
If we have door gadgets,
like that picture,
this is PSPACE-complete: reachability
is PSPACE-complete.
This is a new phrasing of results
from last class.
Actually, we prove this
reducing from pressure plates.
Just another way
to think about the same thing.
Another result we
proved in Lecture 6
is planar reachability,
with say
an antiparallel NAND,
is NP-complete.
So you don't always get
PSPACE-completeness.
It depends what set of gadgets
you're allowed to use.
Often we'll think there's just one gadget
you get to use many times,
but these are two examples.
This one
we guaranteed planar in Lecture 6.
There were no crossings needed,
which is nice.
Cool.
So the point of theorems like this is,
now you have...
you take your favorite video game like
Super Mario Bros. and you have this...
you're going to have a
bouquet of possible gadgets
that would suffice to prove hardness.
So we know if we can build a door,
all we need is a door -- plus a crossover
because this is planar reach...
er, not planar reachability -- then
you prove your problem is PSPACE-complete.
We're going to strengthen
that theorem in a second.
Or, if we can build an antiparallel NAND,
we know that our game is NP-hard.
The hardness goes through.
We're not necessarily in NP.
It depends what game you're making
or what game you're analyzing.
Okay.
But the point of this study,
one point of the study
is to get a whole range of gadgets,
any one of which proves
your problem is hard
so you have more possible goals
of what to build.
There's another fun thing you can do,
which is called simulation.
This is a way to relate gadgets
to each other.
It's closely related to reductions,
and we've actually seen a bunch
of simulations in Lecture 6, for example,
we showed, for example,
if you're given an undirected
noncrossing NAND
you can build in this way
what is effectively
an undirected crossing NAND.
This was a conversion
from noncrossing to crossing;
also works for a match crumblersrs.
This is what we call a simulation.
Let me try to write down a definition,
though an exact definition is a little bit
tedious, I’ll
say what the main parts are.
So we want to simulate gadget G.
We're going to do that
using a system of gadgets,
let's
say gadgets that belong to some family H.
Often this is just going to be
a single gadget, Capital H.
But in general we could use a bunch of
different gadgets to simulate another one.
Plus a mapping
from locations of G
to system locations.
And each location of G should map
to a distinct system
location.
Okay, the idea is, over here for example,
we're trying to simulate a crossing NAND
and these things that are marked in black,
those are supposed to be
the locations that correspond to the four
locations of the crossing NAND right.
So here, it's a connected component,
which is just this one location.
In general,
it might be attached to other gadgets.
But those are the four locations
that correspond, with this mapping.
And then
what we need to satisfy out of this system
is that traversal sequences are the same
or according to the obvious
correspondence between the two.
So I'm not saying
transitions, right:
the internal state of these gadgets,
there's not necessarily
a way to relate them.
But the traversal sequences, that's
what the robot can do,
the agent,
those are...
those need to correspond.
Cool.
So in particular, if you have a simulation
like this, you get a reduction
in the like NP or PSPACE sense,
assuming this...
This simulation is going to have
some constant size, presumably.
So you can just take each gadget
G, plug in the system,
and you get a reduction from reachability
with G to reachability with H.
Hopefully
I got that in the right direction. Yes.
So we get that this these gadgets H are
at least as hard as G.
If G is hard,
we learn that H is hard in the usual way.
So we can use simulations
to prove hardness.
But it's also pretty interesting in its
own right, we're going to see some cool
simulation results.
All right.
So that's kind of the framework,
the general framework.
Now we're going to see a bunch
of more specific results that are
big families of gadgets
that are really interesting.
So let's start with the so-called door
framework.
So we've seen this door gadget.
This is the nth drawing of it,
a little different from before.
Again, I'm
going to draw it as a three tunnel gadget,
but the open could have been a button.
Either way is interesting.
But there are other ways to...
And the edges could also be directed
or undirected.
All those versions are interesting
and PSPACE-complete.
There are some simpler door gadgets too.
So let's say we take the traverse line
and connect it to a close line.
Then we make something
called self-close.
This is a self-closing door.
Still has two states,
but now only two tunnels.
The open tunnel is as before.
If you traverse
it, you go to the open state.
The self-close tunnel is only possible
in the open state: you can't do it
in the closed state, just like traverse.
And when you do it, the door
closes behind you: you transition
to the closed state immediately.
So this is nice.
It's simpler to build a self-closing door
and then a door.
There's only two tunnels instead of three.
And another cool gadget
you get from removing this traversal
in this state.
So then we get this picture
which is completely symmetric between
open and closed.
If I swap open and close,
I get the same gadget.
So they're just labels.
There's basically two tunnels,
exactly one of which is always open.
And in this state, the bottom one is open.
When you traverse it, you switch states.
In this state, the top one is open.
This is a symmetric self-closing door.
And the nice theorem
-- maybe I'll go up here,
adding to our hardness collection
-- is that
planar reachability
is PSPACE-complete
for any door
gadget, just need one of them:
could be a door,
could be a self-closing door,
it could be a symmetric self-closing door,
could have directed tunnels, could have
undirected tunnels, open could be a button
or it could be a tunnel.
All of those are hard
in the planar setting,
which is nice.
Let me first give you another way to think
about these doors is through an example.
So let's play a game.
This is a real video
game called Sokobond, where you...
normally you're pushing around atoms
to make molecules,
but we're going to ignore that mechanic
and we're just going to think of,
you have these big molecules
that move as a single block.
Otherwise it's like pushing blocks.
So this is a door.
We're
going to build one of each of the doors.
So here, for example, we cannot traverse
because this rigid object
is stuck between these walls.
But we can come in this open line
and push the object down
and now it's open.
We can follow the traverse line.
But in order to do the close line,
we have to move
the molecule back where it was.
So we close the door.
Okay, now let's do the same thing,
but with a self-closing door.
So now we're currently in the open state
and we can follow the self-close line.
But when we do so,
we have to push the molecule up to the...
up one, and then we wouldn't
be able to do self-close again.
So we closed, but we could always
reopen from the open line.
And here's a symmetric self-closing door.
Nicely this diagram,
at least the purple part, is rotationally
180 degrees symmetric.
So here we do a self-close
where we push this guy up
in order to get down here
and then symmetrically to do a self-open,
we'd have to go like that
and push it back down
and we would not be able to do an open
move again,
just like a symmetric self-closing door.
All right.
So that gives you some intuition maybe.
This is three different proofs
that this game is PSPACE-complete.
But we can also take our proof
from last class
and say, well,
we just don't need a crossover anymore
because now we know doors
themselves can build crossovers.
So it's enough to just build a door.
Let me show you some more applications,
then I'll say a little bit more
about how we analyze...
how we prove things about doors.
Here is Legend of Zelda: Oracle of
Seasons. It has this cool magnetic glove
where
if you're close enough to a steel ball,
you can pull it towards you
or push it away from you.
And here is a regular door.
This is in the closed state, for example.
It's not possible to do this traversal
because this guy's in the way.
You can't push or pull it here.
And if you try to push or pull from here,
you're too far away from the ball.
There's a limited range,
but you could come
in the open line and repel the ball
and push it down to this state.
Then you're able to do the traverse
and if you want to do the close,
the ball's in the way.
So you have to repel it away from here
and then you can close,
but you'll be over in the state.
Here is a pulling blocks game.
This is Pull!, which means forced pulls.
Whenever I move away from a block
like here, I must pull it with me.
That lets you build
this kind of one way gadget, A diode.
This is actually from a previous version
of this class.
And let me get the URL out of the way.
You can play these games interactively,
these puzzles interactively,
if you click on the links
at the bottom of your screen
below the slide.
So here is a self-closing door.
This is the main self-closing mechanism.
So we come through this diode
and when we walk left, we pull this square
to the left, which prevents us
from going down in the future
until we come to the
open line and pull it back.
So there's a self-closing door
and just a few pictures
you prove that this
game is PSPACE-complete.
Here is Legend of Zelda:
Breath of the Wild.
This also applies to Tears of the Kingdom.
If you have platforms
that you can move around within
some limited range, then in particular,
this is from the actual game.
You can move them around
to get to a desired location.
But that's so here's that lower
part of the level
in order to traverse,
you come through here,
you pick this guy up
and you move it over there.
But then if you leave here, you can't
reset this back to the beginning.
So it's a self-closing door.
And the way to reopen
it is to come through some other path
-- this is not in the actual level
-- and pick this up and move it over.
Because you have a remote control.
You might not be able
to get through this barrier,
but you're able to move the platform over.
So we got a self-closing door.
So PSPACE-complete.
You can also
apply this self-closing door framework
to a whole bunch of 3D
Mario games from Super Mario
64 to Super Mario Odyssey
and even Captain Toad, which is sort of a
Mario game, a Mario inspired game.
Here is the Super Mario
64 [reduction] implemented.
So we have this Boo
and some quicksand/lava that,
if you touch, you die.
And so you can do this
crazy mechanic
of pushing the Boo to the other side.
So we're moving this Boo up here
and then you can actually push it
through a wall
and that sets the Boo for later
traversal down this way.
So this is actually
a symmetric self-closing door.
If if the Boo's here, you can do this
reversal and then you leave here.
You can't actually walk
through the door normally.
But then, if the Boo’s up here,
then you can take it back.
So one of these two traversals
would be possible and it switches
which one is available for next time.
Super Mario Odyssey for fun.
This is a game mostly about alien hats,
but it also has fun characters
like the Jaxi, which is a cat
you jump on and you can ride it
until you hit some bump
and then it stops and stays there.
So this is going to keep track
of which state we're in.
We can ride it to the right.
And this purple stuff is poison,
it kills you.
And so the idea is if you come in here
and you jump on this A button,
it will create this platform
for a few seconds.
Then you ride the Jaxi over and you cross
and then the Jaxi is on the right.
And so you won't be able to do that again,
assuming this is too far to jump.
But later you can come with B, create
that platform, and ride the Jaxi over.
So this is again
a symmetric self-closing door.
So very useful gadgets for proving games
PSPACE-complete.
All right.
So let me tell you a cool
simulation result.
It turns out if you take
any one of the door
gadgets -- door, self-closing door,
symmetric self-closing door
-- each of them can simulate
every other gadget in the universe.
So they are, in some sense,
the most powerful gadgets,
even though they have just a few states
and tunnels.
This example I showed you
of a system of gadgets before
is actually a proof of this theorem.
But I won't cover this form.
I'm going to show you a simpler one
that's kind of nice
using self-closing doors.
And separately,
you can show that every door
can simulate a self-closing door.
Now we're going use a self-closing door
to simulate anything.
But first we're going to simulate
a self-closing door
with a bunch of open lines
and a bunch of self-close lines.
And this is the picture
to make that happen.
So we're...
for a self-closing door,
we're going to use green for open
and purple with an X through it to say,
if you traverse this,
it will self-destruct,
it will close until you open it again.
If it's dashed, it's currently closed.
So all these gadgets are currently closed
and this central one is going to be
controlling the overall state of the door,
whether it's open.
So currently it's open.
So let's say we came through this location
of corresponds to this one
and we open this door.
So one, two, three and four
are all closed, except now we open three
and now we come through here,
we self-close door 0.
So we're going to switch from the open
state to the closed state down here.
And now where can we go?
We could try to go exit
through this location, but this is closed.
Only one of these doors will be open.
And when we when we traverse it here,
it will self-close,
restoring us to the state where [doors]
1, 2, 3, and 4 are all closed.
But we exit at the location
that corresponds to where we entered.
So this is a sort of multiplexer
for self-closing doors.
And now we're going to use that
to build an arbitrary gadget.
Say this three-state
three-location four-transition gadget.
So we're going to
take one self-closing door for each state
and then we're going to have our locations
-- A, B, C -- down here,
and we're going to take each traversal
one by one and just sort of implement it
in the obvious way.
This traversal says that-- sorry,
this transition says that in state
1 we can go from A to B
and we end up in state 3.
So state 1 is here,
we're going to start at A, location
A, and self-close 1 -- that's
only going to be possible if 1 was open.
I didn't mention, but exactly one of these
or at most
one of these [doors]
is going to be open at any moment.
That's what state we're in.
So if we self-close 1,
that means simultaneously
that we were just in state 1,
but now we're no longer in that state.
And then we're going to route that
to an open tunnel for state 3,
because that's
what we want to transition to.
And then we connect that to location B.
And we've implemented that transition.
And we do that repeatedly for each
transition
and they join together at the locations
here.
But that implements exactly the behavior
that you want from the gadget,
because when you're at the same location,
you can do
those transitions.
Cool.
So that's...
Now, of course, when we do this,
we get these self-closing doors
with lots of open lines and close lines.
That's why I needed to build that first.
In general, there are going to be
crossings in this diagram
and I'll just wave my hands and say
there's a crossover
gadget using self-closing doors.
But it's fairly involved -- not what
I want to go through today
-- but it's possible.
And so you get planarity too.
Cool.
We call the door
-- all these door gadgets --
universal
when they can simulate everything.
Cool.
This just
says if you can do a transition,
you can immediately undo it.
If in state q, you can get to state r,
via a to b, then in state r,
you can go from b to a
and you get back to state q
or you can get back to state q.
Pretty natural notion.
We were originally thinking about this
in the context of games
where you can push and pull blocks
where every move is reversible.
There are lots of video games
where your moves are reversible.
It's nice for puzzle games
because then you can never get stuck,
though obviously not all games work
that way.
And I believe all the gadgets we've seen
so far are not reversible.
So here is a gadget that is reversible
and it's an important
one called the Locking 2-Toggle.
It has three states.
These dotted lines are just for intuition
and they don't mean anything.
In this diagram.
There is a neutral
state where two reversals are possible,
these two arrows.
And here let's...
I have an animation of this one.
If you traverse one of these tunnels,
that tunnel reverses direction
and the other one disappears.
So the only thing you can do
from this state
actually is the reverse transition,
which is go back across that line.
Then you're back to the neutral state
and you can choose whichever
one of these you want to do.
It is sort of locking in whether the top
or the bottom was the last thing traversed
from left to right, until you reset it
and then you're back
to the unset state.
So that's a locking 2-toggle.
And it turns out to be important
in the following sense.
So we're going to characterize
exactly when a certain
set of gadgets
have a hard reachability problem,
which is given a set of
reversible
deterministic
tunnel gadgets.
So three requirements
on the gadgets here,
but the main one is reversibility.
Then we're also going to assume
deterministic
and that all of the traversals
are according to tunnels.
Then we have
reachability
is PSPACE-complete if and only if
I give you a few equivalent things.
So the first one is that it's equivalent
to planar
reachability being PSPACE-complete.
So in this setting,
you never need crossovers,
or you always get crossovers
for free: if your problem
is PSPACE-complete, then so is...
if reachability is PSPACE-complete,
so is planar reachability.
And the next one
is that some gadget in your set
has interacting
tunnels.
I think go vertical here.
So interacting tunnels
means that traversing some tunnel
affects
the traversability of another tunnel.
It’s important
that it's a different tunnel.
So it might increase or decrease
the traversability of some tunnel
in some other direction,
but that's all you need.
So this is great.
If I give you a gadget that is reversible,
deterministic, and tunnel,
you can just check every possible
traversal, see in every state,
see whether any one of them
affects traversability of another tunnel
via that transition.
If so, you've got interacting tunnels
and your problem is PSPACE-complete.
Great.
But there's another cool characterization
which is, it’s also the case,
if you ever have gadgets
that are hard, they simulate
a locking 2-toggle.
So this gadget is in some
sense the simplest gadget
that is PSPACE-complete
within this family of reversible,
deterministic, tunnel gadgets.
So in some sense, locking 2-toggle
is the only thing you need to think
about building in your video game.
In practice,
other gadgets might be easier to build
or depending on the game you're doing.
But in a certain sense,
what this is showing is
whatever you can build,
it can also build a locking 2-toggle.
So you could have also built it.
It just might be,
you know, a constant factor larger.
Cool.
So this is when you’re PSPACE-complete.
If you're not PSPACE-complete, you are
polynomial.
In fact,
you're in a smaller class, which is called
nondeterministic log space,
which we won't talk about much
in this class, but it's basically
what you can do with shortest paths.
Cool.
So I want to sketch a proof of this
theorem because I feel like it's pretty
core to how you get to understand
large families of gadgets.
We're taking any reversible
deterministic gadget and use...
that's hard, and using it...
or that has interacting tunnels
-- that's the cleaner thing to say
-- any reversible deterministic gadget
that has interacting tunnels.
We're going to be able to convert it;
we're going to be able to simulate
a locking 2-toggle with it. So
let's do it.
This is a picture of a generic,
in some sense
reversible, deterministic, tunnel gadget
that has interacting tunnels.
So the idea is that
there's some transition, say in state
1, we do this tunnel traversal
and we go to state 2.
And before this arrow was not there,
and after, this arrow is there.
This is generic because we know that,
if you can do this
transition, let's say to state 2,
we know that the reverse is then possible.
So from here you can do two, then
from here you can do you can go to one.
And so if you think of it
going from here to here,
you are adding
traversability of this tunnel.
But if you think of it
going from here to here,
you are removing
the traversability of this tunnel.
So just by relabeling 1 or 2,
this must happen somewhere.
Now, the other stuff,
the empty arrowheads, the question marks,
we don't know whether this traversal
is possible or not.
There might also be other tunnels.
And we're putting question marks to say
we don't know what state happens there
or even whether it's possible,
but this must exist within your gadget.
So now I'm going to use this
to build a locking 2-toggle.
First, we're going to build...
we're going to split into two cases.
What I'd really like is just a directed
edge, an edge that you can't
traverse in some direction, but
you can traverse in the other direction.
Okay, so one possibility
is that exists already in the gadget.
For example,
maybe this empty arrowhead isn't there,
then here's a directed edge
and just kind of ignore
the rest of the gadget and say, here's
the directed edge in this state right now.
You can't go this way.
But you can go this way. After that,
who knows what happens?
But initially it's like that.
Or, that's not in the gadget already.
Then we know that,
if I have this arrow to the right,
there must also be an arrow to the left;
otherwise I had a directed edge.
So I can fill in this arrow,
I can fill in this arrow,
fill in this arrow, and erase this arrow.
Otherwise
I would have had a directed edge.
So my picture now
looks like it's a little more solid.
I know what transitions are possible
among these tunnels.
I don't know what states
some of them go to.
Okay.
But we can take that gadget and just glue
together two of the locations and say
from here to here is a directed edge.
First, you see you can't enter this way.
But I claim
I can go through this way and get out here
because I know that
if I go across this way, I get to state 2.
And then I don't know what state this goes
to, but it is possible to traverse here.
So now this
this gadget is in some unknown state,
but at least it was possible
to go from here to here once.
So I'm thinking that that is a directed
edge.
Okay.
Now we built directed edges, we're
going to build what's called a 1-toggle.
1-toggle is this gadget: very simple state
diagram, two states, one tunnel.
Each time you traverse the tunnel,
it flips states
and also the tunnel flips directions.
So in the left state,
you can only go right to left.
When you do so, you enter the right state
from where you can only go left to right.
This is like one
half of a locking 2-toggle,
without any locking -- hence the name.
We started with 1-toggles,
then we built 2-toggles, and then locking
2-toggles, in the history.
Okay,
so I claim if I take my directed edge
gadget, which you can think of this way,
where in one state
I can't go here, but I can go across here
and enter some other state,
which I don't know a lot about, but I do
know that I can do the reverse traversal.
And the other thing, I have no idea.
Okay,
So I'm going to take two of these gadgets,
one in this first state
and one in this second state,
but reflected, and glue them together
like this.
And I claim this is a 1-toggle.
Let's see why.
First, if I try to go from right to left,
I get stuck.
So I'd have to unwind
and reset everything.
But if I go from left to right
when I traverse here,
I switch to the other state for this guy.
I can go back
and then if I continue,
I go to the other state for this guy,
which is this one flipped.
And so now you see that
it's impossible to go this way.
So the next thing I must do
is go from right to left.
So it's exactly a 1-toggle.
So that's kind of cool.
Now that we have 1-toggles...
Here, I've repeated the directed edge
construction, the 1-toggle construction.
Here are my 1-toggles.
I'm going to glue two of those together
with two copies of the original gadget
here and here.
This one is rotated 180°.
This is fun.
So the claim is this is a locking 2-toggle
in the neutral state.
One thing to notice is
I cannot go this way
because of this 1-toggle, and I cannot go
this way because of this 1-toggle.
There's two traversals
possible: this one and this one.
And they are symmetric.
So let's do the bottom one.
First I go across here, I have...
I enter some weird state,
which I don't know much about.
I do know that there's a return
path, but that's about it.
Then I must go through this 1-toggle.
It does a 1-toggle thing,
and then I go through this gadget.
It transitions to state 1, rotated 180°.
Check it’s this guy.
And now what can I do?
So now
both of these toggles are pointing left
and I can't go this way.
I can't go this way
because I know in this state
there is no arrow in this direction.
That's where we were kind of using
that this arrow disappeared in the state.
So now I can't use the top line at all.
I'm locked.
I also can't go left or right
on the bottom because of this one toggle.
The only thing I can do is unwind
what I just did.
So that's a locking 2-toggle.
Pretty cool.
Okay.
Other fun fact is there...
in the planar setting,
there are many different
locking 2-toggles.
There are three different
locking 2-toggles:
parallel, antiparallel, crossing.
They can all simulate each other.
And then you can build a crossover.
And you also have to prove that locking
2-toggles are PSPACE-hard.
But to do that you need a...
or one way to do it
-- the way we normally do
it -- is the reduction
from Nondeterministic Constraint Logic,
which is what we're covering
in the next lecture.
So I will not show
you a proof of that here.
Instead,
I will show you some applications.
So here is another Legend of Zelda: Oracle
of Seasons mechanic, which is minecarts.
Minecarts are these things
you can hop into and then you ride them
to till you get to a terminal, let's say.
And these green things
you can only traverse
when you're in a minecart,
you can't walk through them.
So in particular, it's impossible
for Link to get through here.
It's impossible
So you have to enter initially
through on this cart or in this one.
This is going to be a locking 2-toggle.
Let's say we go up this one
and now we're able to control this switch
which controls how this track works.
But it's actually how we want it right
now, let's say.
And we can go on this cart.
And when you're in a cart in this game,
you get...
you have almost no control.
So you have to follow the cart
till you get to the end.
Now we're here and we can exit.
Let's say this way.
And the key thing is now
this cart is out of the way.
So it's possible
for Link to exit through here.
And of course you can reverse all that.
Or maybe not, of course,
but you can reverse all that.
On the other hand, if while this cart...
while this cart is down here,
if you tried to do the same thing from
the other side, you can switch the thing
and take this cart here.
But you would bump into the existing cart.
And let's say that's not allowed.
It's a little more complicated
in the actual game.
And so that means you
if this is locked in the left state,
you can't transition into the right state.
until you've unwound
and rode this cart back to here.
But then you have to leave
the way you came.
So you get a locking 2-toggle.
Here is maybe a somewhat easier
one to see -- well, it’s a messier gadget.
This is a different pulling blocks
game called Pull?.
This is with optional pulls.
When you walk away from a block,
you can pull
if you want to, but you don't have to.
This is trickier to show hard.
Here, for example, is a 1-toggle
in that setting.
You have to pull those in order to...
I mean,
you don't have to from the game mechanics,
but you have to in order
to get to the new location.
So you get a 1-toggle.
And out of a bunch of those 1-toggles,
you can build almost a locking 2-toggle.
It starts up a little weird,
but it's roughly a locking 2-toggle.
I've by now shown you a bunch of different
pulling blocks results.
So for fun
I thought I'd show you a table of
basically all the combinations
you could imagine
of the strength of pulls,
whether your pull is optional or required,
whether your game has gravity in it.
So, like, all of these reductions,
for example, work even if the
the blocks are subject to gravity,
because they're all supported from below.
But I am
I allowing fixed blocks
in all of these games.
If you don't have fixed blocks,
most of these problems are open.
So basically
all of these are PSPACE-complete.
This is also from an earlier version
of this class, a bunch of students
from that class,
except there's one which is Pull?,
so optional pulls, strength
one, fixed blocks, gravity.
That combination we know is NP-hard;
that was actually in Lecture 6.
But we don't know
whether it's PSPACE-complete.
We do know it’s PSPACE-complete
if you allow thin walls or strength 2
and so on.
So mostly settled for pulling blocks.
All right.
Any questions?
Take a little break.
So the next topic.
Oh, sorry.
I have one more example,
which is pivoting robots.
These are robots that can spin around
edges.
They exist in real life.
And you might want to know,
given two configurations of these robots,
can I go from one to the other?
Can I reconfigure from one
to the other while...
with the whole super robot
remaining connected at all times?
This turns out to be PSPACE-complete via
a very beautiful
but also complicated reduction from
using locking 2-toggles, building
a locking 2-toggle.
Here even building
a branching hallway is kind of tricky,
because you have to be sure
to maintain connectivity
of all the robots, but it can be done.
Also for hexagons.
I think these makes
some pretty nice diagrams for gadgets.
Okay.
Yeah.
[AUDIENCE] You said we want to
reconfigure from one state to another.
[PROFESSOR] Right, good question.
[AUDIENCE] But here we’re just
getting an agent...
[PROFESSOR] Yes, so what I’ve...
everything I've been talking about
so far has been about...
I think I erased it.
I've been talking about reachability
which is, can a robot
get from one spot to another?
Here we're interested in reconfiguration
where we want to actually
we're given a target state
for every gadget in the system.
Maybe not even a target location
for the robot.
And there is a paper which I'm
not going to talk about much here,
but I did want to mention
about reconfiguration
instead of reachability
and often reachability
Often reconfiguration is also hard
in particular for reversible gadgets.
It turns out,
if the reachability problem is hard,
then reconfiguration is also hard.
Among other things.
Sometimes reconfiguration is easier,
sometimes it's harder, than
reachability in general.
But reconfiguration with locking
2-toggles is also hard.
And that's what we're using here.
Cool.
Thank you.
Uh, right.
One more thing.
In the reversible
deterministic gadget setting,
here are some more gadgets
for you to play with.
Of course, locking 2-toggle
sort of the main one that matters.
But if you think about the two-state
two-tunnel gadgets,
which does not include the locking
2-toggle because that's three states,
there are only a few different things
you could have on each tunnel.
You could have a toggle where every time
you traverse it, it changes directions.
You could have an edge that does nothing.
Those aren't really interesting.
I would call those trivial.
It's always available or never available.
You could have a lock where -- this is
like the traverse line of a door --
where in one state you can go through it
and the other state you can't.
And you could have a tripwire
where it's always traversable
and every time you traverse it,
it changes the state of the gadget.
So you can take -- for two tunnels
-- you take any pair of these.
It turns out every pair
of nontrivial tunnels
is PSPACE-complete,
in any of the planar orientations.
So in particular,
there's a nice one called the 2-toggle.
This actually predates
the locking 2-toggle, but
it's in some sense, yeah, a little less
fundamental than the locking 2-toggle.
In fact,
these gadgets can all simulate each other.
So they're kind of equivalent
in the hierarchy of gadgets.
but are locking 2-toggle
cannot simulate this.
These are not as basic as the
as a locking 2-toggle. Okay.
And an application of this, for example,
is building a 2-toggle
in another Oracle of Seasons mechanic,
which is these 4-spinners.
A 4-spinner is either blue or red.
When it's blue,
if you visit it, it traverses
counterclockwise
and then it switches to red.
And if you come back when it's red, it
will it will move you clockwise.
So it's a reversible gadget.
And so maybe unsurprisingly,
you can use this reversible setup
and you can build the 2-toggle
ultimately out of four 4-spinners,
which is kind of cool.
Or here is a
turnstile mechanism, which appears
in a bunch of different games,
including Super Mario Odyssey,
where when...
You see there's a little pivot here.
When I walk through this turnstile,
it rotates 90 degrees.
And you can
use that to build a crossing 2-toggle
or an antiparallel locking 2-toggle.
So having all these different gadgets
that are hard is useful.
Sometimes it's easier to build one
than the other depending what game
you are building things in.
Okay,
next topic is pushing blocks,
so we talked about pulling blocks a bunch.
This is a slide from Lecture 4,
I think, where we have
lots of hardness results.
We've only talked about the NP-hardness
results so far.
I want to talk about this one
-- PSPACE-completeness of Sokoban --
and this one, which was an open problem
back when we recorded Lecture 4,
but is now known to be PSPACE-complete,
using gadgets
and a particularly interesting
aspect of gadgets
called checkable gadgets.
So let me show you that.
First, let
me tell you a little bit about Sokoban.
I think you know the rules already.
It's like Push-1F.
So you can... there are fixed blocks.
There are blocks
you can push one at a time.
But instead of the usual goal
-- with Push-1,
the goal is to get the robot from A to B
-- with Sokoban, you have a bunch of dots
on the playing field and you need to
cover every dot with a box,
and number of dots equals number of boxes.
So this is an old game
and exists in a zillion forms.
And it was proved PSPACE-complete.
This is one of the first
PSPACE-completeness results
for a puzzle game, I believe: 1997.
It was proved by this guy, Joe Culberson,
who was on the Chinook team
that solved 8 × 8 checkers in 1992.
And then, in my head,
Joe was like looking for
the next game to solve.
And so he looked at Sokoban
and proved PSPACE-completeness
by building a Turing machine in Sokoban.
It's a very complicated
and cool reduction.
But with a modern lens
-- we have lots more technology now
for proving PSPACE-completeness
-- it turns out just one of these gadgets
in his picture is a self-closing door.
And so that one gadget
we now know proves PSPACE-completeness,
even in the planar setting.
So let me show you how it works.
It's built out of a few subgadgets.
The first one is a diode.
So this is a gadget
you can traverse from left to right,
but not in the other direction,
provided that gray block stays
in one of these two spots
which in Sokoban is easy to force by
just saying it must return to this spot.
In Push-1F,
we're going to have to worry...
I'm going to try to adapt this proof
to Push-1F.
In Push-1F, we have to worry about
wedging the block into the corner.
Then this gadget is completely open
and broken.
So we're going to avoid this.
But for now it's a diode in Sokoban.
Next gadget is a 1-toggle.
Okay, we know what a 1-toggle is.
This is a nice way to do it.
And in Sokoban,
It's easy to force these blocks
to stay away from each other
and on these little tracks.
That's the gadget
in Sokoban, where they each
have a dot underneath them.
And you can see to get here,
I have to move these blocks
in pairs to the right.
And then if I erase these two squares
out of the 1-toggle,
I get what we call a precursor.
It's a little weird.
It behaves like a 1-toggle down here,
but you can always escape to the top.
So the way I like to think about it
is it remembers the last time you exited:
did you exit on the right last
or exit on the left last?
And if you last exited on the left,
you cannot enter on the right.
That's how a 1-toggle works.
So when we...
we're going to draw this gadget like this.
This actually is a nontunnel gadget
because you can get...
this location is reachable
from both this one and this one.
This is not a tunnel.
I'm going to draw it like
this little T with an arrow saying
you cannot currently enter from here.
So this arrow can move over here.
Then if I leave this way,
then the arrow will move over here
to say
you cannot enter this way, like a toggle.
Okay, so now I claim
if I combine these gadgets in this way
with the precursor in the center,
two diodes and a toggle,
this is a self-closing door.
So let's just walk through it.
First, the self-closing is down this path.
So I walk through the diode,
I walk through the precursor,
which toggles it to the other side.
Then I walk through the diode. Great.
Now I won't be able to do that again
because that arrow blocks me.
And if I want to open, I can come down
from the top, which toggles that guy.
I could go over to the right here
and leave, but it would leave this toggle
in a bad state,
which in Sokoban we can just prevent.
We'll have to worry about that later.
The intended solution is you go over here
which toggles this
and then you leave up the top
because you can always leave up the top.
So now you've reset this to an open state
and that's back to how it was.
And now you can self-close again.
So self-closing door,
Sokoban is PSPACE-complete.
Let's try to make it work for Push-1F.
So we're going to take
initially this
diode
gadget, and we have these intended uses
-- where you use it
like a diode -- and these breaking uses
-- where you wedge it into the corner --
and we're going to focus on
just these top three rows of the diagram.
And what I'd like to do is force the block
to stay on this little track.
And I'm going to do that by saying, well,
at the end of my construction, somehow
I'm going to force the robot to have to go
through this traversal
from this location to this location.
I don't know how they go inside,
but you must go from here to here
and then you must go from here to here.
And if the block is wedged
in one of these corners,
one of these traverses will be impossible.
So I'm going to forbid
these broken uses by saying at the end,
you must do these checking traversals.
If they're impossible,
you won't be able to solve the puzzle.
If they're possible, you'll be okay.
And so we can basically assume
because we know this is coming at the end,
we can assume we're in these good states
where things are not broken.
So that's the intuition.
Let me write down a.
theorem,
or I guess a definition and a theorem.
We're going to call
this not a diode, but a checkable diode,
so that you can get diode
behavior, provided
you check it at the end.
So a checkable G
is going to consist of another gadget...
So G is a gadget and it's a checkable G
If we have another gadget
G’ plus a sequence of traversals,
which we call
check traversals,
such that
G equals G’
restricted to good states
where check traversals
are possible.
So a gadget has a bunch of states,
I'm going to call it a state good
If it's possible from that state
to do the check reversals
in order, and broken otherwise.
And I would like one thing which is,
if your gadget is in a broken state,
it stays broken, no matter what you do.
So we want broken states
to be closed
under traversals.
Which is true, for example,
in this gadget:
if you wedge the block in a corner, it's
not getting out.
So once you're broken, you stay broken.
So I'm going to say...
So this is a checkable
whatever-this-gadget-is --
if I add the rows, it becomes a diode,
but it's not quite a diode yet.
Because these traversals
are going to be possible
only in the states where this block is
in one of those two spots.
And so it's going to act
like the top diagram, not like the bottom,
as a checkable that-gadget.
Great.
So what?
Cool thing is planar
reachability
with G
reduces to planar
reachability
with G’, together with
two gadgets MSC and SO,
which are these gadgets.
I don't really want to say much about them
other than they're very simple.
You can only...
they only have like one or two transitions
and then they're dead.
So they're relatively easy to build in in
a lot of games, or that's the hypothesis.
So if we ignore those for a second,
what this is saying is reachability with G
-- which is like the diode, say, the diode
we want to build,
but we don't know how -- reduces
to reachability with our checkable gadget.
So that's great. It's...
we can pretend that
we actually had the gadget
that we wanted,
where we've restricted to the good states.
Even though we don't know how to build it,
we know that at the end
we'll be able to force
all the checking reversals to happen.
That's where we use these other gadgets.
The way we prove this is,
at the end of the construction,
when you reach the original goal,
we're going to wire things up
so then the robot is forced
to basically close off
all the old transitions
that were possible, and only enable
the checking traversals,
and then force those checking traversals
to happen in order.
And then there's the real goal.
And so the only way to get there will be
if you actually kept
every gadget in a good state.
So I'm not going to prove that,
but that's the intuition.
So let's apply this
to Push-1F.
So first you have to build
those little gadgets: SO and MSC.
It's doable
with some pushing blocks technology.
Now we get this fun operation,
which I didn't name it yet:
we're calling postselect.
That's the restriction to good states.
We're just only considering the gadget
with the subset within the good states.
So we apply that to this piece of a diode.
We then force the block
to be on this little path,
and then we add
these two rows at the bottom.
Now we have an actual diode
or checkable version of that.
Okay, let's do it with the precursor.
Precursor has the same issue.
You can push these blocks into the corner
and it would just be completely open.
So we're going to focus on the bottom
three rows here and also add a couple of
pathways.
Then we're going to add these
to check traversal, say at the end
we must have that.
And then that prevents blocks from being
wedged in these two spots in the corner.
So now we know, by postselection,
we can assume that the blocks
stay within here.
Then we're going to add these two
checking reversals
that will prevent these blocks
from being mushed together.
And it will,
yeah, force them to be on their
individual tracts here
and not adjacent to each other.
Great.
So now we have this gadget
and we just add the rows above and below.
And that's exactly how the precursor
is supposed to behave.
in Sokoban.
But we built it as a checkable
gadget in Push-1F.
One more use is in this:
when we were building the self-closing
door, I said there's this weird thing
you can do,
where you leave out here and there's...
you left this gadget in a weird state.
In fact, it's a broken state.
If you add this checking traversal
-- at the end, you need to go through here
-- that's only going to be possible
if you didn't leave this toggle
in a broken state.
And then, once you're
in this broken state, you stay broken.
And so if we do postselection,
that can’t happen.
So now we have a Push-1F self-closing door
in the checkable sense.
So this is not a standard simulation.
We can't simulate G
with G’.
We call it a nonlocal simulation,
because we're not just plugging in
one little thing for the gadget.
We're actually modifying the whole graph.
But it's basically, for purpose of
hardness, is just as powerful
and it lets you solve
big problems like Push-1F.
Cool.
So I have a couple more topics,
but I'm just going to sort of show
you them very briefly, just as pointers.
If you run into gadgets like this that you
think might be relevant to your problem.
The first one
is I/O gadgets,
and in particular
the idea of zero-player motion planning.
So far there's been a robot that can make
decisions that could go left.
They could go right.
So you have a kind of
nondeterministic system.
With I/O gadgets,
you have the potential to make everything
completely deterministic.
What the agent does is determined at
every stage, with the right assumptions.
But first,
an I/O gadget is when you can partition
the locations of the gadget
into two types: inputs,
which are just entrances -- places
the agent can go in -- and outputs,
which are places
where the agent can go out.
But crucially, no location
you can both go in and go out.
Okay.
All traversals
must be from an input to an output.
And in addition, we're going
to require,
on the system,
that there's at most one input
in each system location.
Okay.
So this was a constraint on the gadget.
This is a constraint on the system
to say that whenever.
So I have some gadgets wired together.
Here is a system location
I want among all these locations.
At most, one of them to be an input
so that if I'm the agent,
there's only one place I can go.
Let's say this is an input.
So then I have to go in here and I
have to do a transition within this gadget
and then whatever location I'm in next,
there's only one input,
so I've got to go there.
So this leads to what we call
zero-player motion planning.
And now you can still call it
reachability, but it's more like,
do I reach not can I reach
because it's determined what happens --
if the gadget is deterministic,
it's determined what happens.
So this is removing
nondeterminism in the connection graph,
and if the I/O gadget is deterministic,
then I also have no nondeterminism
within the gadget.
There's one other constraint
I want, which is output-disjointness,
which is this here: no two inputs
traverse to the same output.
So for a given output, there's
only one input that could lead there.
And I'm going to restrict it two states.
So I think this is the set of adjectives:
two-state, deterministic,
output-disjoint input/output gadgets.
In that setting, all of our gadgets
are made up of little pieces like this.
So let's start with maybe the switch.
The switch,
there's two states up and down,
and in the up state, I'll
go to the top output -- this is an input
-- and in the bottom state,
I'll go to this output.
This is a tunnel actually
where whenever I traverse it,
I go to the top state.
This is a toggle.
So every time I traverse it,
it switches states.
This is a set up switch. So
this is just like the switch
-- when I enter here and the top state,
I'll go here; in the bottom state,
I'll go here
-- but in the bottom state,
I will also change to the top state.
So it always sets me to the up state.
It's like the fusion of these two gadgets.
Of course, there's also the set-down
and set-down switch.
And finally there's a toggle switch
where, when I enter, in one state,
I leave here, and the other state,
I leave here.
And in either case, I switch states.
Now, these two are special:
we call them unbounded.
Because potentially, you could...
if you have...
if you don't have these,
the number of state changes you can do in
your gadget is bounded
because this doesn't change the state,
this always sets it
up, this always sets it up.
So those
are kind of less interesting
and put your problem in NP.
But these unbounded things are more
interesting and can get you PSPACE.
So in particular,
we have this theorem,
which is among two-state
deterministic output-disjoint I/O
gadgets, we are PSPACE-complete
if and only if there's an unbounded
piece
and there's more than one
nontrivial input.
I forgot to even mention
the trivial inputs; trivial inputs are
where they always do the same thing,
so they're not interesting.
This is assuming NP does not equal PSPACE.
So this is in some sense the gadgets
you care about, for PSPACE-completeness,
are when you have an unbounded piece and
you have at least two of those subunits.
Yeah?
[AUDIENCE] If you have a set-up
and a set-down line on the same gadget,
does it count as unbounded?
[PROFESSOR] I was wondering that.
[AUDIENCE] Yes. [PROFESSOR] It does count.
Okay, sorry.
So this picture is incomplete.
Also, if you have a set-up and a set-down,
or like a set-up switch and a set-down,
or something, that's also unbounded,
because you can then change the state
as many times get.
I was wondering that as well.
Uh, the only bounded case is when all the
things point in the same orientation
and you don't have any toggles Cool.
Great.
I guess that is captured by this diagram,
though there's a lot of words
in this diagram.
In particular, zero player
-- this is the zero-player row
-- unbounded multiple non-trivial inputs,
you get PSPACE-completeness.
If you're bounded and zero player,
you only get P-completeness.
Now, you could also relax this restriction
of at most one input
in each system location,
and then you get nondeterminism
in your system again.
Then you're one player and then you still
have PSPACE-completeness here, naturally,
but you do get NP-completeness
in the bounded case.
All right.
One more fun fact
is that,
among these gadgets
-- two-state deterministic
output-disjoint gadgets --
every one of them
can simulate every other,
and furthermore, they can...
you don't have to have
all those adjectives.
All of those gadgets can simulate
every deterministic I/O gadget.
So that's
pretty much this whole zero-player family.
So this is an example.
Here this is clearly answering
the question of unbounded.
We have a set-up line and a set-down line.
Alternatively,
these two could be replaced by a toggle.
Those two gadgets
can simulate every deterministic
I/O gadget.
So they're universal,
but they're also kind of a basis,
because they can also simulate each other.
So that's pretty nice.
There's a similar thing
for the bounded case.
And in the one player
setting, this gadget...
so when you remove the restriction
of every system location
should have at most one input,
this gadget can simulate all gadgets
just like the door.
So that's nice.
There's also a cool open problem here,
which is
what if you only have a single input?
And I think the interesting case here
is the toggle switch,
where every time you enter,
you leave on the opposite location
and you can build
exponential behavior here.
But the problem is
probably not PSPACE-complete because
it's in NP intersect coNP and
some other things,
but it's open whether it's NP-hard.
Probably it's not,
because it's in NP intersect coNP, but
exactly what it's complexity
is remains a mystery.
All right.
The last...
Oh, then you can apply
this zero-player stuff
to show that actual games are hard.
There are a lot of video games
that involve simulation.
Like you design some stuff
and then you just want to know,
does it achieve my goal?
For example, Factorio, you can prove
NP-hardness of the train mechanism...
sorry, PSPACE-hardness of the train
mechanism using
these gadgets.
Okay.
And the last topic,
I just took my handwritten notes
and put them up here
so I can say it really quickly.
I wanted to tie together
this motion planning or gadgets
framework we've been talking about,
with the stuff from Lecture 6.
Whereas now in the class, we're thinking
about mostly unbounded mechanisms,
unbounded systems/puzzles, where we get
PSPACE-completeness, in Lecture 6,
we were all about NP-completeness.
And there's a nice gadget theory related
to that, though it's not exactly...
it doesn't exactly cover what's in Lecture
6, so I have a comparison here. So
there's this notion of DAG gadgets.
Let me...
I did not actually include the definition.
So a DAG gadget.
DAG means Directed Acyclic Graph.
This is where the state-transition graph
is acyclic.
This is not a graph
we've talked about yet.
The state-transition
graph has a vertex for every state,
and it has an edge
for every possible transition,
ignoring the locations.
So you just merge
all the locations together and just say,
what could I possibly do from this state?
What states could I get to?
That must be acyclic.
This is a very strong property.
It says that the number of transitions
you can do in
your gadget is bounded:
it's less than the number of states.
You run out of states
because you can't cycle.
So in
that setting, if you also assume
your gadget is a tunnel gadget.
So among DAG tunnel gadgets,
the reachability problem is NP-complete
(we can't we don't know about /
this doesn't apply to planar reachability,
just reachability) is NP-complete
if and only if one of two things happens.
And these will sound familiar
because they're like door
opening and door closing,
but they're slightly different.
So the easy one is distant opening.
This is, there's some traversal
that opens a different tunnel.
So this is my picture
of the generic setup.
There's some traversal
you can do that switches to an O state
which opens.
This wasn't possible before.
Now it's possible.
Who knows what else happens.
This is related,
but not the same as from Lecture 6.
We saw opening doors with one button
which I would draw this way.
We haven't drawn it
as a state diagram before,
but we have a button that transitions
to the open state.
And in this state you can traverse it
many times.
That's something that's not possible
with a DAG gadget because you can only...
this one will self-destruct at some point.
You won't be able to do
any more traversals.
This is a slightly more general form where
the gadget becomes eventually
static and stops changing,
but you can still re-use it.
But morally they're kind of the same.
Just one's a
tunnel instead of a button.
The other option is a little trickier
to define roughly.
It's that when you do a traversal,
you're forced to close something else.
But it's a little subtle
because you could close a tunnel
in one direction and not the other.
And so it turns out what's the right
definition is: there's
some orientation on the tunnels, say
all of them left to right --
but it doesn't have to be that --
and there's a traversal that
closes at least one
different tunnel in that direction,
in that orientation.
So here's a weird, nondeterministic gadget
where this is true.
There's a traversal up here
that goes to c or d: state
c for Closed and state d for closeD.
And in this
one, we
closed this tunnel in this direction
and in this one
we closed this tunnel in this direction.
So that would be an example.
It's forced that you closed something but
it's not forced exactly what you close.
That turns out to be exactly
what makes this problem NP-hard.
And we can compare that to the closing
door.
Well,
there are various closing door gadgets.
But one of them was when you traverse
this, you close the other path.
This is quite a bit more general
form of that.
But again, here
we're only thinking about DAG gadgets
where everything self-destructs.
Here it's something called LDAG gadgets,
where you also allow loops.
These have not been fully characterized
in terms of NP-completeness,
whereas these have.
And if you're not NP-complete,
you're in NL again.
So that's
the short story about bounded gadgets.
If you're interested in more,
you can check out the corresponding paper.
This is one of the first papers in gadget
theory.
You can generalize a lot of this
to the LDAG scenario.
For the distant opening, though,
we only know how to prove hardness...
if you have a distant opening LDAG,
we know how to prove hardness only
when you also have a no-return gadget.
Just like we needed with the opening door
with one button
in the nonplanar scenario.
The just in closing,
just like with the closing door,
you can always prove
no hardness with LDAGs.
So a lot of this DAG theory
applies also to the LDAG theory,
which is nice.
Great.
That is whirlwind tour of the general
theory of motion planning gadgets.
Very powerful for proving hardness
of your favorite motion planning problem,
where you have an agent running around
interacting with local state.